<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practice of the Exchequer court, with its severall offices and officers being a short narration of the power and duty of each single person in his severall place. Written at the request of the Lord Buckhurst, sometime Lord Treasurer of England. By Sr. T.F. Whereunto are added the rules and orders of proceedings by English bill.</title>
            <author>Osborne, Peter, 1521-1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1928_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8740</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873381</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125850</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125850)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 239:E1928[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practice of the Exchequer court, with its severall offices and officers being a short narration of the power and duty of each single person in his severall place. Written at the request of the Lord Buckhurst, sometime Lord Treasurer of England. By Sr. T.F. Whereunto are added the rules and orders of proceedings by English bill.</title>
                  <author>Osborne, Peter, 1521-1592.</author>
                  <author>Fanshawe, Thomas Fanshawe, Viscount, 1596-1665, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 160, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for Tim Twyford and W. Place, and are to be sold at their shops within the Inner Temple gate, and at Grays Inne gate in Holborne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identified on UMI microfilm (Early English books) as Wing F420.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May".</note>
                  <note>In Bodleian Library copy Table (A-M) appears at the beginning and (N-Z) is bound at end; in British Library copy the entire Table appears at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Bodleian Library (Early English books), and the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Exchequer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:125850:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE PRACTICE OF THE EXCHEQUER COURT, With its ſeverall OFFICES and OFFICERS.</p>
            <p>Being a ſhort Narration of the Power and Duty of each ſingle Perſon in his ſeverall Place.</p>
            <p>Written at the requeſt of the <hi>Lord Buckhurſt</hi> ſometime Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>T. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto are added the Rules and Orders of Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings by Engliſh Bill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>Tim. Twyford</hi> and <hi>W. Place,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops within the Inner Temple gate, and at Grays Inne gate in Holborne. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:125850:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:125850:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader,</head>
            <p>I Have neglected ordinary flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, leaſt I might ſeem to beg an applauſe, not merit it. Let it not ſeem a work of ſupererroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to publiſh this Tract ſince tis hoped the Work it ſelf is <hi>bonum &amp; utile,</hi> elſe had not that great and wiſe Lord <hi>Buckhurſt</hi> taken ſuch care to command it to writing, had he not known that <hi>bonum quo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munius eo melius;</hi> And therefore I hope my ſelf very worthy of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe from blame by any, inaſmuch as hereby preſent generations may learn paſt Polity, and by the Rule thereof ſquare their actions. And
<pb facs="tcp:125850:3"/>
if any thing herein fall ſhort of expectation, tis my requeſt, That you will rather look at it as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape then a crime; ſince the whole ayme is both thy pleaſure and profit, which if you attaine, I have the accompliſhment of my hope; otherwiſe,
<q>
                  <l>—Si quid noriſti rectiusiſtis,</l>
                  <l>Candidus imperti, ſi non his uters mecum.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125850:3"/>
            <head>What every of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the EXCHEQUER uſually do by virtue of his Office in <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Lord Treaſurer.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Queſtions concerning the Lord Treaſurers Office, with ſeverall Anſwers to every Queſtion, made by <hi>Mr. F.</hi> Or rather a Declaration of his Opinion touching the ſame; written at the Requeſt of the Lord <hi>Buckhurſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="question">
                  <head>I. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lord Treaſurer is ſworne and admitted in open Court by the Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor or Lord Keeper for the time being.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:125850:4"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> Sir, I have ſeen the Records of the like Admittance, and yet the Lord Treaſurer that was laſt, was ſworne in the Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="question">
                  <head>II. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee is appointed by Statute co be at the election of the Sheriff yearly,</hi> In Cr. Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> By the Statute of <hi>Anno</hi> 14 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. The Chancellor, Treaſurer, and cheife Baron, calling others to them, are to name Sheriffs in <hi>Cr. Animarum</hi> yearly, and by the Act 12 <hi>R</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. they muſt be ſworne to do as is there limited.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="question">
                  <head>III. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee nominateth after the Sheriffs be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, all the Eſcheators in</hi> England.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> Eſcheators ought to be nominated by virtue of the ſayd Statute of <hi>Anno</hi> 14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. but by what reaſon he doth it alone, I know not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="question">
                  <head>IV. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He giveth by Statute all the Offices of the Cuſtomers, Conmptrollers, and Searchers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125850:4"/>
through</hi> England <hi>during pleaſure, by his Warrant under his hand, directed to the Lord Chancelor or Lord Keeper for the time being.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> This he doth by virtue of a Statute made 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="question">
                  <head>V. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee granteth by Statute and Cuſtome, for the accuſtomed Rent,</hi> Cuſtodiam <hi>of the ancient Crown Lands, and Eſcheated Lands, and</hi> Firman ulnagij, <hi>in all the ſhires in</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> I cannot ſpeake certainly of this, I know not how to informe my ſelf ſo as I would, ſaving that I thinke the Alnage is let to Farme by the Statute of <hi>Anno</hi> 4 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. and 4. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="question">
                  <head>VI. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He granteth,</hi> Firman terrarum ſeiſ. pro Domino Rege quamdiu in manu dicti Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis fore contigerint, <hi>to any that ſue for it, by his Warrant made of late to the Clarke of the Pipe, and in old time directed to the Lord Chancellor or Lord Keeper for the time being.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:125850:5"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> Neither do I know this certainly, but I have beene told, that the Leaſes made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Exchequer ſeale be not good.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="question">
                  <head>VII. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſitteth in Court or in the Exchequer Chamber, and ordereth with the Chancellor, under Treaſurer, and the Barons of the Court, the matters offered before them, to the Princes moſt benefit as they can by the law courſe, or equity, but the Judgement is only,</hi> Per conſiderationem Baronum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> Hee ſitteth in the Court, and ordereth with others, as is declared in this Article, when it pleaſeth him, and the oftner the better, for the profit and ſervice of the King, and the diſpatching of ſuits and ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="question">
                  <head>VIII. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee may call upon the Kings learned Councell and the Officers of the Court, to conſider by the law and Preſidents any matter ſore preſſed againſt his Majeſty at the Barre, and deſire the Court to stay pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in it while they may be better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:125850:5"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> There is no doubt but hee may and will do all this, when hee ſhall ſee others negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent or any other good cauſes ſo to do.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="question">
                  <head>XI Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee and the Barons may by Statute ſhall debts of three hundred pound and under to be payd at dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> This they may do by the Statute of 1 <hi>vel</hi> 2 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="question">
                  <head>X Queſtion:</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Treaſurer, the Chancellor, the Vice-Treaſurer, and Barons of the Court, may and do uſe to make Orders and Decrees, of Allowances of Penſions, Portions, Rents, Payments, Fees, and Conſiderations thought good by the Court, and upon intricate mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and matters of equity in the Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the King and the party to bring them to a finall end as beſt for all parts and not well able to be determined by the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleading, or otherwiſe of the Court.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> They may and do uſe to make Orders and Decrees as is there declared, and for that purpoſe do ſit both in the Court, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125850:6"/>
often in the Exchequer Chamber, to heare Engliſh ſuits, which they do by virtue of the Statute, 33 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 39. See the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute booke at alrge. <hi>fol.</hi> 92. <hi>H.</hi> 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="question">
                  <head>XI Queſtion</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee in giving judgement with the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the Court, doth order, ſtay, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, heare, debate, prolong, and end, all cauſes of the Exchequer, either by Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, order; or decree, by privy ſeale from his Majeſty, when otherwiſe it will not be done.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> It is certaine that hee and the Court, or to ſay more plainly the Court (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is cheife) may do all lawfull things that are there to be done, either by virtue of Law, or of the Kings Warrant, which I take to be the meaning of this Article.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="question">
                  <head>XII Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He alone puniſheth, reformeth, directeth, and ordereth all the Officers of the ſame, that by Law are not to be brought into the Court of Exchequer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> All the puniſhments which I have found in any Record, have beene done as by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125850:6"/>
Court, and all their Accounts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealments, Informations; and ſundry other things, have been taken, examined, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as by the Court: And yet his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath great Authority over them by the Statute of 17 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. where it is enacted, that thoſe Offices ſhould remaine in the Kings hands under the governance of the Lord Treaſurer for the time being, with the aſſent of the Counſell where need ſhall be.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="question">
                  <head>XIII Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee directeth his Warrants to all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers (as the caſe lyeth on any of all their ſides) for all manner of Commiſſions, Proceſſes, and Injunctions needfull in the matters of the Court, and when the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth ſpeed, hee writeth firſt his Letters therein, and if hee thinke it good, hee ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Commiſſions, Proceſſes, and Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after them, and ſometimes by the ſame, doth undoe and ſtay that the Barons have commanded, Judgement being not given.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> He directeth Warrants for Commiſſions and proceſſe, and ſo do others, but they be taken and uſed as Acts of the Court and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125850:7"/>
allowed and diſallowed, as they ſtand with Juſtice. Hee ſometimes maketh Warrants for injunctions to ſtay ſpoiles of houſes, woods, and ſuch like, &amp;c. But for alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of poſſeſſions from one to another, <hi>Non auditis partibus,</hi> or out of Court very ſeldome or never. As for writing of Letters and after proceſſe, I thinke they have been few of late yeares, and found almoſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. For, <hi>Super debile fundamentum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit opus.</hi> And of the undoing and ſtaying of the Barons Commandements, hee hath given ſometimes ſtay for a time upon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter information then they had, but undone nothing but upon conference with them, and with their Conſents to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, I have only ſeene theſe things done, but not found them in any Record that I rember.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="question">
                  <head>XIV. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee ſendeth his Serjeant at Armes for all ſuch as do diſobediently ſet, neglect, or deviſe to diſappoint the Kings Proceſſe, and ſometimes hee ſendeth him otherwiſe after his diſcretion for perſons that are skipping aſide, erneed ſo to be ſtayed, or to be ſent for.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:125850:7"/>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have not ſeen any Record that he hath ſent a Serjeant at Armes for any man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Marqueſſe his time, and that was done when ordinary proceſſe would not be obeyed, and that alſo very ſeldome. But in the Lord <hi>Burleighs</hi> time, the ſending grew common againſt Sheriffs and Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as I remember I have ſeene in ancient Records, that Serjeants at Armes have been ſometimes, and yet ſeldome au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed by commiſſion to doe ſundry ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="question">
                  <head>XV Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee alone giveth the Warrant to all men to have their Wine free of impost.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer</label> Hee alone (for any thing I know) hath given all the Warrants for freeing the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt of French Wines, yet I finde in <hi>Anno</hi> 1571. the impoſt was rated by writing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Majeſties hand, wherein it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that if any of reputation (being good houſe-keepers) were left out of the rates, then it ſhould be lawfull for the Treaſurer and Chancellor to give allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but how this authority hath beene put in ure I know not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="question">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:125850:8"/>
                  <head>XVI Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He, the Chancellor, and Vice-Treaſurer, make all Warrants for wood ſales.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> I have not ſeene or found any Record, or otherwiſe, that hee or any other of the Exchequer, hath had any authority to make ſale of the Kings Woods, but by Writ or Commiſſion under the great Seale, and that alſo very rarely, but by Article, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Articles for annexing of the Court of augmentations to the Exchequer <hi>viz. Article</hi> 27. there is a prohibition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Woods of the Lands in the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of the augmentation Court of this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, <hi>viz.</hi> No Wood ſales to be made without a Commiſſion from the Lord Treaſurer, and to ſuch other of the Court as hee ſhall call unto him, and in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the under Treaſurer calling unto him two of the ſame Court, and other Authority then this I have not ſeen, but to the Court of generall ſurveyors, which (as I take it) is ſince diſſolved by the ſtatute, 7 <hi>E.</hi> 6 <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="question">
                  <head>XVII. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee, the Chancellor and Vice-Treaſurer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:125850:8"/>
make all Warrants for mony to the Receivor, of the ſhire, for reparations of houſes, Sea-Bancks, and water works, where the ſame be. And commonly he directeth his Warrant for a Commiſſion to go out to enquire of the ſayd needfull reparations, and the charges of the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> All the generall Authority that I have ſeen to give warrant for reparations, is by the Articles of annexing the ſayd courts before mentioned, <hi>Article,</hi> 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="question">
                  <head>XVIII Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He directeth Warrants ſometimes to make Commiſſions to ſome to be Receivors, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyors and ſuch Officers of the Revennues, during pleaſure under the Exchequer ſeale, after any be dead, or put out for any miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors whilſt the Kings Majeſty be moved for the Bill aſſigned, and to ſtay others from ſuing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> He ſometimes alone, and ſometimes with others, hath made ſuch warrants as is alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and not without good cauſe as is there mentioned.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="question">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:125850:9"/>
                  <head>XIX. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He cheifly protecteth the Iuriſdiction of the Court, the Officers, and all the matters of the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> The Juriſdiction, Officers, and matters of the Court be protected by the law, and by the Authority of the Court, and this Lord being the cheif, doth cheifly worke in that matter, like as in all other wherein he dealeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="question">
                  <head>XX. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He Commandeth and reſtraineth all the Officers and Miniſters of the Courts, and all others in the Kings Majegiſty Cauſes, and matters, belonging to the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> He commandeth all to do their duties diligently, juſtly, and truly, and reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all to do the contrary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="question">
                  <head>XXI Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He alone and the Chancellor Vicetreaſuror and Barrons of the Court, after his and their diſcretions, do puniſh all the miſdemeanors of the other Officers, and Miniſters, of the Court, and of all others that abuſe the Court,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:125850:9"/>
the Cauſes, the proceſſe, and appendance of the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> I have ſeene by Records that the Court hath done puniſhments after divers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners upon the Officers and divers others, but I remember none on Record to be done by him alone.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="question">
                  <head>XXII. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He untill the late uniting of the Court of Augmentations, and the firſt fruits and Tenths, did uſe to ſit, and deale very little in the Court of Exchecquer, but left all there belonging to him, to be ordered by the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, Vice-treaſuror, and Barons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> I thinke this to be true, but I have not ſeen any Record of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="question">
                  <head>XXIII Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He alone, or he, the Chancellor and Vice-Treaſurer, do allow at the</hi> Liberate <hi>every</hi> Hillary <hi>and</hi> Trinity <hi>Terme, ſuch ſummes of mony out of the Exchequer, as to them ſeems good for any bodies conſiderations, about the ſervice and charges of the court or Revenue of the ſame, as by the leiger privy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:125850:10"/>
Seale in the receipt he and they are authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed ſo to do.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> He and the under treaſuror, or one of them alone without the Chancellor, do give theſe allowances in ſuch terme or time as they ſee cauſe, by vertue of the privie Seale in the Article mentioned and for this purpoſe, the Articles of the annexing of the Augmentation Court, Article, 20 may be conſidered.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="question">
                  <head>XXII. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He alone by the Articles of the late court of Augmentation, and the firſt fruite and Tenths annexed to the Exchequer may do ſomething alone, and ſomething he with the Chancellor, and under-treaſuror, the Chamberlaines and Barrons of the Exchec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer or three of them and ſome things he with the Court, and ſome things he with ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as he ſhall call to him, which are here too long to ſet downe particularly, and therefore are referred to the ſaid Articles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> The certainty whereof may be knowne by the Articles themſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="question">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:125850:10"/>
                  <head>XXV. Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee hath uſed before the uniting of the ſayd Court of augmentation:, and the firſt fruits and tenths in all great matters of the Courts, ſometimes to confer with the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor and under Treaſurer alone, and ſome times with them and the Barons, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with them and the Kings learned Councill, and ſome times with them all, and the two Remembrancers and Clerke of the Pipe about the ſame, what were beſt to be done. But ſince the uniting of the ſayd Court, according to the Articles of uniting the ſame, he hath uſed much to conferre and joyne with the Chancellor and Vice-Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, upon all forraine matters, Cauſes and Actions of the Court, that ſtand not in plea, Suits or Judgement before the Court, but come in queſtion, order, and determination by the ſayd union, and ſhall call ſuch Officers as ſhall pleaſe them to conſider and determine upon the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> I have ſeen no written direction for this courſe, but undoubtedly he may and will call any Officer unto him to conferr with for his Majeſties ſervice, and determine of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:125850:11"/>
matters according to Juſtice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="question">
                  <head>XXVI Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee alone, and he, and the under Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer by his diſcretion (as I take it) do ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey and order all the Receits, and all the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and matters thereof, and of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, and do direct payments, and ſtayes of payments by their diſcretion, and do exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all receits coming in, and going out of the receit, but can ſuffer no penny to go out but by privy Seal or great Seale from the Prince, or by decree, or Writ from the Court, that ſometime cometh ſo about by the Judgement of the ſame. He hath divers other authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by old and new Statutes both alone and with others, which are referred to be found out by learned Counſell that have abridged the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwer.</label> I have not much experience in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, but I do hold it for certainty, that none of the Treaſure may be payed out, without good warrant from the King. And I have ſeen by record, and otherwiſe, that ſome miſdemeanors there committed, have examined and ordered in <hi>Superiori S.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <p>Here I was required (as I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:125850:11"/>
by the Meſſenger, to ſet downe by what Warrant and authority, the things before ſpecified were done. I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to performe that according to my beſt underſtanding, as before appeareth. And where I was required alſo to ſet down, what other authorityes be in this Lord; ſo it is, that I <note place="margin">Authorities in the Lord Treaſurer.</note> have obſerved by reading of the Records of all Kings times, that he hath been taken for a very great Officer, and chief of the Exchequer, amongſt which concerning his ancient ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Authority and Duty, I finde theſe words written of him, <hi>Adquem spectat de commodis domini Regis curare, &amp; ut ejus diſdendia viteut prospicere,</hi> By which, and by his oath, his generall duty and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, may be conveniently and reaſonably conceived and gathered. And touching his other authorities that be not before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I thinke there be ſome by Statutes and ſome by Commiſſions or privy ſeales, concerning his Office in the Exchequer, which I do not take upon me to ſet downe leaſt I by forgetfullneſſe, ſhould omit ſome of theſe I know, and might omit diverſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:125850:12"/>
others, having not beene made acquainted with them, and to my beſt remembrance, they be moſt of them joynt with others, and am of opinion, that if (when any thing ſhal be offered unto him, or required of him to be done) It will pleaſe him firſt to require the ſight and underſtanding of his War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, in that behalfe his Lordſhip ſhall in ſhort time finde and know his authorityes that hee will require in ſuch caſes, whether it be by Act of Parliament, or any other way; and I for my part will be ready to declare my ſimple knowledge and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in every caſe.</p>
                  <p>And what hath beene done by the two laſt Lord Treaſurers, I ſuppoſe that the next hath ſeene either already, or heard himſelfe, or ſhall by ſome other hear of it. And if his Lordſhip ſhall finde juſt cauſe to underſtand by what Warrants and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they did ſo, he may eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of it by ſome of his Majeſties Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:125850:12"/>
               <head>The Chancellor.</head>
               <p>HE is an Officer thought by many to have beene placed in the Exchequer, to have qualified all matters of extremity and rigour between the Prince, the Subject, and the party, with Conſcience and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, But yet I never ſaw nor have heard of any Record ever made in the Exchequer in that caſe, by order, direction, or qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>He hath in Court the proper place of the Bench above the Lord Treaſurer. He (in the Lord Treaſurers abſence) doth in Court in the Exchecquer Chamber all things to the Kings moſt benefit and furtherance.</p>
               <p>He in the Lord Treaſurers abſence, if the Barrons and learned Counſell of the ſuitor doe much preſſe any matter againſt the King, or that he findeth there is ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the caſe, doth pray that it may ſtay untill the Lord Treaſurer be made privie, and the Kings learned Councell may be conferred with, and the preſidents of the Court may be ſhewed upon the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:125850:13"/>
He maketh warrants to any of the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embrancers to make all manner of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions proceſſe, and iniunctions, as the caſe requireth, aſwell as the Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror doth.</p>
               <p>He by the late Lord Treaſuror, and Sir Richard <hi>Sackvills</hi> order and agreement, had referred unto him the overſight and rule of the Court of firſt fruits and Tenth of all compoſitions, bonds, mattes and canſes of the ſame.</p>
               <p>He in the Lord Treaſurors abſence for orders and Commandements in Court for the benefit of the Prince, and caſe of the Subject and ſuitors, hath ever done com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly that the Lord Treaſuror uſeth to do.</p>
               <p>He hath ever uſed in great cauſes of the Court, to make the Lord Treaſuror privie, and to confer with his Lordſhip about the ſame.</p>
               <p>He being Vice-treaſuror alſo, after the death of the Lord Treaſuror, and while a new Lord Treaſuror be made, doth all things which the Lord Treaſuror both in the Exchequer and Receipt doth uſe to do</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:125850:13"/>
               <head>Under-Treaſurer.</head>
               <p>IS an Office erected of late in the time of King H. 7. And whether it was of the Kings nomination firſt, or of any Lord Treaſuror, it is not known. But it is ſaid that Sir. Robert Mitton Knight, that was then the Lord Treaſurers Remembrancer, was the firſt Vice-treaſuror that was ever made, and had no patent thereof; but <hi>Sir.</hi> Iohn Baker when Thomas Duke of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke was made Lord Treaſuror in H. 8. time, being nominated Vice-treaſuror after Sir. Robert Mitton did procure a Patent thereof under the great Seale of England and was the firſt that had a Patent of the ſame office.</p>
               <p>He in King H. 7. time (as I have heard ſay, the report of the remaine of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the receipt being brought then to the King at the end of every Terme) did cheſt the ſame up, and did Content every Cheſt what ſumme and ſorts of mony was in it, intitleing it B. or C. as in courſe it fell out, and carried it to the Kings Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuror in the Tower, and entred the ſame in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:125850:14"/>
the Kings Book which he kept in his deske, leaving ever in that receipt ſufficient mony to pay ordinary Fees, and ſums of money it was charged with betweene that and the next Terme. And hereupon I thinke the Vice-treaſurer was made to ſee this done, both of truſt and eaſe of the Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, as being too mean a thing for his Lordſhip to be troubled with, and yet fit to be done by ſome meaner perſon of truſt, and great ſecrecie.</p>
               <p>He being Chancellor of the Court in the late Lord Treaſurers time and abſence, and before the uniting of the ſaid Courts of Augmentation, and the firſt fruits and Tenths, did order and command all things as the Lord Treaſuror in the Court of the Exchequer, and in the receipt, ſaving that which was done <hi>Per Conſiderationem Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronum,</hi> upon Pleas, Informations, Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He before the uniting of the ſaid Courts, and ſince the Lord Treaſurors death, did make the two Praiſors of all wares, and Marchandizes ſeized by any Informer, as taken up uncuſtomed, and informed againſt in the Court of Exchecquer, whereof they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:125850:14"/>
make him a Bill of Praiſement, and he giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth order whether the owners ſhall have the goods againe as they are prayſed; or whether part or all ſhall be otherwiſe ſold, wherein the late Lord Treaſurer would ſometimes deale and intermeddle with his privity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Lord Chiefe Baron.</head>
               <p>HEE is ſworne by the Lord Chancellor or Lord Keeper for the time being, or the Lord Treaſurer, and the other Barons, and is the cheife Judge of the Court, and in matters of Law. Information and plea, he anſwereth the Barr and all ſuitors.</p>
               <p>He giveth all days for bringing of Pleas, Informations, Anſwers, Replications, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynders, and amending of the ſame, as occaſion is offered at the Bar.</p>
               <p>Hee maketh all the Orders of the Court that touch or concerne the matters at the Bar, or the Suite depending in Court, or is moved by learned Counſell, and yet with great orderly conſent of the Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, the Chancellor, the Vice-Chancellor,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:125850:15"/>
Vice-Treaſurer, the other Barons, and the Kings learned Councill, or ſuch as are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of them, as the caſe ſhall require.</p>
               <p>Hee in the abſence of the Kings learned Councill, anſwereth the Bar moſt diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Kings Majeſties behalfe, and when the Kings learned Councell be there, hee ſuffereth them to ſpeake and anſwer to the Bar for his Majeſty all that come, and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with them my ſpeech and conference, to ſatisfie the Bar, to alter or mend the matter or words of the plea, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of his Majeſties ſide, in all cauſes the Law will bear him.</p>
               <p>He, before hee proceed to Judgement in Cauſes againſt the King, either hee asketh or willeth the Officer on whoſe ſide the matter is, to aske the Kings Attorney what he can or wil ſay more for the King in ſuch a matter, that the Court may be informed of it. And even ſo doth he for the party, if the Kings Majeſty be to have Judgement for him.</p>
               <p>He and his fellowes conferre together in all difficult matters and judgements of the Court, and when they have reſolved the Law therein, they uſe to impart the ſame
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:125850:15"/>
to the Lord Treaſurer, Mr. Chancellor, Mr, Vice-Treaſurer, and to the Kings lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Counſell, and if they cannot ſatisfie the Barons, the Law to be otherwiſe, they proceed to Judgement. The Court being called upon therefore at the Barr, although the Lord Treaſurer, Chancellor, Vice-Treaſurer, and the Kings learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, would faine have it goe otherwiſe, which they do with great circumſpection, and feeling ſometimes the opinion of the Judges therein, and ever after long and often deliberation had firſt thereupon.</p>
               <p>Hee ever giveth Judgement in the Term time only, and ſpeaketh in this wiſe to the Remembrancer, on whoſe ſide the matter is. If the Kings Attorney ſay nothing for the King between this and ſuch a day, for ſuch a matter, enter Judgement for <hi>I. S.</hi> or if the party ſay nothing for ſuch a matter, enter Judgement for the King.</p>
               <p>He in open Court awardeth Commiſſions Proceſſes, Injunctions, and all manner of Writs, and commandeth ſtay and <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeas</hi> of the ſame, and ſuch his Award is ſet down in the booke of orders on the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers ſide where they iſſue out.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:125850:16"/>
and ſuch his Award is ſet down in the book of Orders, on the Remembrancers ſide where they iſſue out.</p>
               <p>He out of Court maketh Warrants and Fines, as the Lord Treaſurer, Chancellor, and Vice-Treaſurer doth to any the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers whom it concerns to make out any manner of Commiſſion, Proceſſe, Injunctions, <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> Writs of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Hee in open Court doth ſet Amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Fines upon all Sheriffs, Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Eſcheators; Commiſſioners, purſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, makers and ayders of Reſcues, that do not execute, ſerve, return, deliver, or obey the Kings Commiſſions, Proceſſes, Injunctions and Writs, as to every of them appertaineth.</p>
               <p>He committeth to ward in open Court, and in the Exchequer Chamber, all that be indebted to the King, that misbehave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Court, that diſobey the Kings Proceſſe, that keep not their dayes or the order of the Court, or otherwiſe, be worthy to be committed as the caſe ſhall require.</p>
               <p>He alone in the afternoones in the Term time, doth ſit upon all <hi>Niſi prius</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:125850:16"/>
in the <hi>Guildhall,</hi> that came out of the Remembrancers Office, or the Clarke of the Pleas Office, concerning any matter or tryall there by the Jury of <hi>London,</hi> which cannot be diſpatched at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for lack of time and leiſure.</p>
               <p>Hee appointeth the dayes and Termes when all Demurrers in Law ſhall be argued at the Bar, and likewiſe in the Court to ſhew their opinions upon the ſame.</p>
               <p>Hee commandeth all the Officers under the Bench to make ſearches for the King, and the Court to give their attendance on the Barons in the afternoones at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> to ſet Fines and Amerciaments on the Sheriffs, and to informe the Court of that is meet, or otherwiſe to confer with them. And ſometimes hee commandeth the ſayd Officers to attend at his Chamber upon him and his fellowes, for conference or information about ſome ſpeciall matters appointed there to be heard or conſidered upon.</p>
               <p>He and his fellowes take without Fee in open Court, all manner of Recognizances for the Kings debt, for appearances, for obſerving orders, for keeping the decrees
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:125850:17"/>
of the Court, and ſuch like and for every Recognizance taken out of the Court, he hath ſix ſhillings eight pence.</p>
               <p>He taketh the preſentation of all Officers in the Court, that are under himſelfe and of the Mayors and Sheriffs of <hi>London,</hi> and giveth ſuch exhortation and oration as to himſelf ſhall ſeeme meete, and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their Oathes to be read unto them by the Kings Remembrancer, and ſeeth them take the ſame.</p>
               <p>He taketh the Declarations of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſed Accounts of the late Augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Revenue in the Counties of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland, Richmond, Durham,</hi> Receivers of <hi>Nottingham</hi> and <hi>Derby, Lincolne. &amp;c.</hi> Receivors of <hi>Cheſter, Lancaſter, Weſtmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Cumberland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Receivers of <hi>Northton</hi> and <hi>Rutland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Receivers of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> and <hi>Warwick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Receivers of <hi>Salop, Wigor, Stafford,</hi> and <hi>Hereford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And made before him by the Auditors of the ſame Shires,</p>
               <p>He with the Kings Attorney <hi>Promiſſis Parcandis,</hi> doth ſet all the Fines of Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition upon any that is informed againſt in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:125850:17"/>
that Court by any popular Action, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Statute, which Fyne doth bring the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant to an end thereof, and is ſet downe from the Roll of the Kings Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers ſide, and charged in the Pipe, where he hath his <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> upon his Fine payed by tallie and allowed there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The ſecond Baron</head>
               <p>IS he that is next in place, and Ancientie to the Lord Cheife Baron, and in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence doth Anſwer the Barr in matters of orders, and courſe, as the caſe offereth, and in matters of law, difficultie, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, He referreth all ſuitors untill the Lord Cheife Barons comeing, and that the Court be fuller. He, and his fellowes in the Lord Cheife Barons abſence, in meane Cauſes and matters of Courſe, doe take order with all ſuitors, and matters offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at the Barr, as in dayes of Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, Recognizances, Receiving and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Pleas, informations, lycenſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and ſome Iudgments the Cauſes being
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:125850:18"/>
not great, and the Lord cheife Barons mind being ſomewhat fore-known therein, And in every thing he uſeth more Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in the diſpatch of matters in the Court, which are called on at the barr when the Chancellour, the Vice-treaſurer, the Kings Attorney, or Sollicitor, or ſome or moſt of them are preſent in Court, wherein he and his fellowes have the more conſent and agreement of the cheife Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Court.</p>
               <p>He and his fellowes in my Lord cheife Barons abſence, may doe all in Court that my Lord cheife Baron may doe, and is good in law <hi>Per Conſiderationem Baronum,</hi> though there be but two of them, yet in moſt matters, and eſpecially of any weight, they take a reſpit, and put over the ſame, and wil be adviſed thereof until ſuch a day.</p>
               <p>He giveth yearely the morrow after <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Judes</hi> day, the Oath to the Lord Mayor and Eſcheatour of <hi>London,</hi> that he ſhall make a true Account of the Eſchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip, and aske no petition or Allowance, but that which is good and true.</p>
               <p>He in the Lord cheife barons abſence doth take all manner of Recognizance in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:125850:18"/>
Court, and out of Court, as the Lord cheif Baron doth, and hath for his Fee of every one taken out of Court ſix ſhillings eight pence as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>He taketh the Declaration of ingroſſed Accounts of the Receivors of the late Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation Revenue in the Countie of <hi>Kent, Surry,</hi> and <hi>Suſſex.</hi> Receivers of <hi>London Middleſex. Hertford</hi> and <hi>Eſſex.</hi> Receivers of <hi>Norfold</hi> and <hi>Huntington.</hi> Receivers of <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Receivers, and made before him by the Auditors of the ſame Shires.</p>
               <p>He examineth the letters, and caſteth up the ſums of ſuch Sheriffs forraign Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, Eſcheators Accounts, Collectors Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, of Cuſtomes, Subſedies, and Fifteens, as are brought unto him by any of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors of the Court, in the head of which accounts, the Barons name is ſet that exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, And his addition thereunto is <hi>Auditor,</hi> And then the Auditors name that did take and ingroſſe them, is ſet under the Barons name, and his addition thereunto is <hi>Clericus;</hi> So as it ſeemeth, the old courſe of Exchequer accounted the three under Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:125850:19"/>
the Auditors of the court, and thoſe we now call Auditors, but as their Clerks. And in this wiſe the old account of the Ward Robe, the Victualls, the Ships, the Workes, the Proviſions, the Wars, and ſuch like, were heretofore taken and examined, which be now taken by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors of the Preſts, and are declared by them, and they account before the Lord Treaſurer, Chancellor, and Vice-Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer only, except they pleaſe to call ſome of the Barons to them, as they uſe ſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when the moſt of them cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the hearing of the ſame accounts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The third Baron.</head>
               <p>IS hee that is third in place and Anceintie to the two Barons, and may do all things in Court, in their two abſences as the two Barons, and their fellowes might do before; but in both their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences, the third is very circumſpect to do or meddle with anything, but that which is ordinary, and referreth over all ſuitors as before.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:125850:19"/>
He may take Recognizances in Court to the Kings uſe, as the other did before, and hath his fee alſo of ſix ſhillings eight pence for the ſame, that are taken out of the Court, as the other had before.</p>
               <p>He giveth every <hi>Symon</hi> and <hi>Judes</hi> day the Oath to the Lord Mayor, and Gaugers of <hi>London,</hi> that he ſhall make a true account of the ſame, and aske noe petition or allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance but what is good and true.</p>
               <p>He taketh the declaration of the ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed accounts of the Receivers of the late Augmentation Revenue in the Counties of <hi>Somerſet</hi> and <hi>Dorſet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Receivers of Cornwall, and Devon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers.</p>
               <p>He likewiſe as the ſecond Baron did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, examineth the letters: and caſteth up the ſums of ſuch Sheriffs forraigne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, Eſcheatours accounts, Collectors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, of Cuſtomes Subſidies and Fifteens, as are brought to him by anie of the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Court as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:125850:20"/>
               <head>The fourth Baron</head>
               <p>IS alwayes a Curſiſtor of the Court, and hath been choſen of ſome one of the Clerks in both the Remembrancers offices, but moſt uſually he is, and hath been choſen of ſome one of the Clerks of both the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers office, or of the Clerke of the Pipes office.</p>
               <p>He taketh Oath every <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Judes</hi> day of the two Attorneys, the new Lord Mayor then putteth in, <hi>ad recipiendum man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum Curiae,</hi> And likewiſe of the Deputie Eſcheator and Gauger of the late Lord Mayor, Elcheator and Gauger of <hi>London,</hi> that they ſhall make a true account of the ſaid Offices, and aske noe petition or Allowance, but that which is good and true.</p>
               <p>He if he preſent in Court at dayes of prefixion, taketh the Oath of all high Sheriffs there, under-ſheriffs, or Attorneys, and of all Eſcheators, that they ſhall make a true account of the ſaid Offices, and aske noe petition or allowance but that is good and true.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:125850:20"/>
He taketh the Oath of all Collectours, Countrollors, Surveyors, and Searchers, of all the Cuſtome houſes in <hi>England,</hi> that they have made true Entries in their Bookes without concealment, or leaving oat any parcell of wares, or merchandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, to the Kings hinderance or prejudice.</p>
               <p>He taketh before the Court commonly begin to ſit, or when it hath little to do, or my Lord cheife Baron is abſent, the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals of the Shiriffs, of their ſummons that come in, and are ſworne to account as before, which is nothing elſe but oppoſing of every Sheriff, what he will ſay to every ſummons, which is written to him out of the Pipe, who upon the ſayd oppoſalls an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth unto ſuch ſums as hee will pay and charge himſelfe with, confeſſing ſo much due or received. And to the other ſumms he will anſwer, <hi>O. Ni.</hi> as confeſſing, <hi>On<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur niſt exoneretur,</hi> and ſo the ſaid Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron goeth on in this manner, queſtioning and asking of every Sheriff, what hee ſaith to every ſum in his ſummons, untill he hath gone through every one of them.</p>
               <p>Hee informeth the Bench and the Kings learned Councill from time to time, both
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:125850:21"/>
in Court and out of Court, what the courſe of Exchequer is, and ſtayeth the reſt of the Barons, and the Kings learned Councill, from ordering any thing they go about contrary to the ſayd courſe, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the ſame, and to ſave the Kings Prerogative and benefit, which the courſe of the Court moſt commonly maintaineth and reſpecteth.</p>
               <p>Hee taketh the declaration of the ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed accounts of the Receivors of the late augmentation of the Revenue of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Yorke,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Receivers of <hi>Oxon</hi> and <hi>Berks,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Receivers of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee likewiſe (as the two other Barons) examineth the Letters, and caſteth up the ſums of ſuch Sheriffs forraigne Accounts. Collectors accounts, of Subſidies and Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teens, as are brought unto him by any of the auditors of the Court, and cauſeth his name, and the auditors name that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſeth it, to be ſet with additions of the auditors, and <hi>Clericus</hi> as aforeſayd.</p>
               <p>He taketh the Bayles of all Sheriffs, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs of Liberties, and Eſcheators that keep
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:125850:21"/>
not their dayes of prefixions, but come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Court by attachments, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but with ſureties to be ſworne to account, and then aſſeſſeth the Fines of all ſuch Bayliffes. <hi>Pro libertate reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda,</hi> and of all ſuch Eſcheators for their contempts which be very ſmall, and never above five ſhillings, but rather under, as twelve pence, two ſhillings, and three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings foure pence. And for the Sheriffs Fines, in is ever five pounds a day for his four next dayes after his day of prefixion that he faileth to come and to be ſworne to his account.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The two Chamberlaines</head>
               <p>HAve their place next in Court to the foure Barons, and may ſit and keepe their places dayly in Court if they like to attend and hearken to the cauſes of the Court, without any intermedling therein. But at the election of the Sheriffs yearely, <hi>(In Cr. Animarum)</hi> they are ordinarily to be there, and keepe ſtill their place, and may ſay their opinions for preferment or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:125850:22"/>
ſtay of men to be Sheriffs, as the Barons and Juſtices do, but other dealings in the Court of Exchequer at this day, I know not that they have.</p>
               <p>They have in old time had great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Receit (as I have heard ſay) and have kept certaine keyes of the Treaſury Coffers, and were ever privy to the Pells of Receit, and to the Pells of <hi>Exitus,</hi> of the which each of them kept a controller, as at this day they do of the pell of receits, and no mony iſſued out of the Receit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their privity, as is manifeſtly proved, becauſe at this day every privy ſeal for the payment of any mony out of the Receit is directed <hi>The ſaurarijs &amp; Camerarijs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They have the charge of the Treaſury with the Lord Treaſurer, and keepe the keyes thereof, where all the ancient leagues betweene the Kings Progenitors, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes and States, either do or ſhould lye, and where the booke of <hi>Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> and the ancient Records and Pleas, <hi>De Juſticiarijs itinerant.</hi> and <hi>De foreſt is,</hi> and of diverſe other matters do remaine; into which Treaſury, neither they nor their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties can come with their keyes, untill the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:125850:22"/>
auditors of the Receit come with the Lord Treaſurers key to the ſame that remaineth in his keeping to my Lords uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Kings Attorney</head>
               <p>IS the ſpeciall Officer of the Court that is made privy to all manner of pleas that be not ordinary and of courſe, that riſe upon the proceſſe of the Court, and to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications and Rejoynders growing upon the ſame on any of the Remembrancers ſides.</p>
               <p>He putteth into the Court of his owne name for the King, all informations of concealments of Cuſtomes, Subſides, Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Receits, and of Intruſions, Wars, Spoiles, Incroachments, and Anoyances, done upon any of his Majeſties Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, Woods, Rents, Rights, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments, and upon any popular Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, penall Statutes, Forfeitures, or breach of Covenants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:125850:23"/>
               <head>The Kings Remembrancer.</head>
               <p>THE Kings Remembrancer of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, who at certaine dayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed in the Terme, calleth to account in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Court by his booke yearly made, and commonly called <hi>Statutus magnorum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putantium, &amp;c.</hi> all the great accountants, as the Cofferer, the Maſter of the Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe, the Maſter of the Horſes, the Keeper of the Scudry, the Maſter of the Revells, the Clarke of the Hamper, the Butler of <hi>England,</hi> the Treaſurer of the Mynt, the Lieftenant of the Tower, the Conſtable of the Tower, the Lieftnant of the Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the Receiver of the Ships, the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualler of the Ships, the Maſter of the worke, and ſuch like; and by the ſame booke, ſhould call the Vulgars to account, that are now reduced to a fee farme certain by my Lord Treaſurers Bill made therefore to them for one and twenty years or more, and ſo they anſwer yearly their fee farm in the Pipe.</p>
               <p>And by the ſame booke he calleth (as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:125850:23"/>
before) at dayes prefixed, all ſearchers, <hi>Ad reſpondendum Domino Regi medieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem omnium foris fact urarum in Officio ſuo contingent.</hi> &amp;c. And all collectors of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and Subſidies, <hi>Ad computandum,</hi> which book of States hath all the ſayd Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers chriſten names, and ſurnames, with the addition of their Offices that be full and given, and being not given nor full, nor account at this day, it hath only the Office name in the ſame.</p>
               <p>He inrolleth, and after writeth out the ſame, according to the courſe of the court, againſt all the ſayd accountants that come not in at their dayes prefixed, and account for their ſayd Office, except ſuch as be not now accountants before the ſayd Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons.</p>
               <p>He calleth to account in open court by his like booke called the States of the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors of Subſidies and Fifteens, all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of high collectors thereof granted by Act of parliament in every ſhire, city, Burrough, Towne corporate, and place whatſoever through <hi>England,</hi> as they are appointed and certified by the commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners every where for the aſſeſſing and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:125850:24"/>
of them, and according to their dayes of payment appointed them by the Statute.</p>
               <p>He inrolleth and maketh out proceſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch of the ſayd Collectors for their Bodies, Goods, and Tenements that come not in to account, and pay their mony ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the grants of the ſame.</p>
               <p>He taketh Recognizances to the Princes uſe before the Barons in open Court, or out of Court before ſome one of them, of all ſuch perſons, for moſt cauſes, with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reties and ſeldome without ſureties, as by occaſion of any of the premiſes, or from time to time for any debt day of Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or other commandement of Court, are forced to be bound any manner of way.</p>
               <p>He upon the breach and not keeping of theſe Recognizances, inrolleth proceſſe, and maketh out the ſame againſt all ſuch perſons as were bound therein, according to the courſe of his Office.</p>
               <p>He as the Returnes of the ſayd proceſſe by courſe of the Court do offer occaſion of ſome change of Writs in manner and forme by the Returns of Sheriffs, as <hi>Non
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:125850:24"/>
ſunt inventi, Nihil habent, mortui ſunt, languidi ſunt in Priſona,</hi> and ſuch like without number, doth by and by on the back ſide of the Writ ſo returned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſed what is to be done, or leaveth it to the Clarke of his Office to do it, whoſe charge it is to write the proceſs of the ſhire where it runneth, that of courſe can tell what to do, and all the ſayd proceſſes be ſtill current every Terme untill they that are bound, or their Executors, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators, Heires, or Ter-Tenants come in and pay the mony, or take order therefore, or plead in diſcharge of them.</p>
               <p>He hereupon informeth the Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, and in his abſence, or by his order the Chancellor or Vice-Treaſurer of the Court, every Terme when he is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, of all manner of debts and arrerages of any the ſayd Accountants, or upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other perſon depending in his Office, by reaſon of any the ſayd Recognizances, or of Bonds taken, or delivered in his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice by any other occaſion, and due with them ro his Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Hee according to their Order ſtayeth or ſetteth forth proceſſes for the ſayd debts
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:125850:25"/>
and arrerages, and admitteth any perſon vexed with proceſſe from time to time to plead in diſcharge thereof, or of any part of the ſame, unto which plea the Kings Attorny is made privy, who referreth the ſame over to the Court, if hee thinke not good to confeſſe it.</p>
               <p>Hee hath all manner of Informations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on penall Statutes, Intruſions, Counceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſuch like, put in and ſued in his Office only, with all matters, Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances and Bonds depending or proceeding upon the ſame.</p>
               <p>He by calling on, and remembring the Court and the Kings Attorney of the ſame and other Pleas depending in his Office, doth drive them to be ended, either by the Attorney generalls confeſſion, or Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Court, upon Jury, Demurrer, Privy ſeale, or compoſition, <hi>Pro miſis Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candis,</hi> being upon popular actions.</p>
               <p>He only on his ſide maketh the Bill Roll of compoſitions, <hi>Promiſis Parcandis,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on penall Lawes; and Statutes, and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Lord cheif Barons, the Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney, and the other Barons hands to them, and maketh up the Records of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:125850:25"/>
Hee taketh the ſtallment of all debts by Recognizances after the ancient courſe, and ſometimes now by Obligation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the parties (bound upon their pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) would have out their Bonds again, which elſe be as Statutes of the Staple to the Prince by Act of Parliament, which ſtallments ſhould be forthwith ſent downe into the Pipe, that they might be ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out there for time to time againſt the day that any payment ſhal grow due, and ſo is the ancient courſe of the Court.</p>
               <p>Hee only taketh Bonds and Recognizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Court, and all to the Kings uſe, of all Sheriffs, Cuſtomers, Controllers, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, Bayliffs and of all other perſons whatſoever, that are bound in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and doth all things proceeding upon the ſame.</p>
               <p>He inrolleth all the ſayd Bonds and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizances in remembrance of the yeare, that are taken there or brought in, and delivered in Court for the Prince his better ſafety, if the ſame ſhould miſcarry by fire imbezeling, or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Hee ſometimes by Warrant of the Lord Treaſurer and in his abſence the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:125850:26"/>
the Vice-treaſurer, the Kings Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and the Court, maketh out Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Countrie to certaine Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by <hi>Dedimus Poteſtatem</hi> to take Bonds to the Kings uſe when the partie is to be bound with Suretyes, and cannot conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently come up, or bring his Sureties hither to be bound for him, of the Retorne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he maketh Record, and fileth the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and the Certificate and the lands beſides,</p>
               <p>He by like writt changeth bonds and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizances of the firſt parties that were bound and taketh others in other places, that the Lord Treaſurer the Chancellour and the Vice-treaſuror alloweth of.</p>
               <p>He maketh all proceſſe, Commiſſions, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, orders, Awards, and Entries proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or growing of anie matter, cauſe, plea, or originall depending, or to be ſued on his ſide, that the whole Courſe of the matter may appear and remaine on Record in any place ever together.</p>
               <p>He maketh a Record in his office of all the Certificates delivered unto him by the Clerke of the Star chamber under his hand, of ſuch fines as be felt upon any perſon by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:125850:26"/>
the Lords there, and cauſeth the ſame fines to be ſent downe from his Record into the Pipe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſumoned out there, to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from thence by the Treaſurors Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer when they be put in his Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cedula Pipe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He maketh up the Record of every Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops death, of his multure of his beſt horſe, Ring, and cup of gold, and ſilver, ſeiſed to the Kings uſe, or of fine made thereof by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their executors or the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of their goods and Chattells.</p>
               <p>He taketh the Proffers every <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme, in the Receipt before the Barons, of all the Sheriffs, Bayliff, and Eſchearours and marketh the default of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of them that doth not appear there by his Attorney, aſwell as the Treaſurors Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer doth.</p>
               <p>He readeth in open Court the Oathes and the Uſher giveth the Book at the Election of Sheriffs yearely every <hi>C. Animarum,</hi> in French, and offereth the Book to be kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them that choſe them.</p>
               <p>He readeth in open Court the Oathes and the Uſher giveth them the Book to kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that all the grand Officers of the Court
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:125850:27"/>
of Exchequer doe take either before the Lord Chancellour for the time being, and the Barons, and likewiſe the Oathes that all the under Officers Miniſters and ſervitors of the ſaid Court, doe take before the Lord Treaſuror, the Chancellour the Vice-trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuror, and the Barons of the Court, or ſome of them.</p>
               <p>He onely maketh the great Prerogative Writ of the Court, for all Officers, Miniſters and Servitors of the Exchequer, and Receipt, and for their men that be ſued elſwhere in anie Court of Record or place to remove ſuch plaint before the Barons ſuch a day to ſurceaſe the ſuite.</p>
               <p>He hath delivered into his office to keep, all manner of Judgements, Fines Recoveries, deeds, Releaſes, writings, Charters, and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences whatſoever, that are brought into the Court by the Lord Treaſuror, the Kings Attorney, or any other perſon, either for the Aſſurance of lands and Tenements to the Crown, or for the better Recoverie and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying lands, and tenement that ought to come or be in the Crowne.</p>
               <p>He maketh by warrant of the Lord trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuror, the Chancellor, the Vice-treaſurer,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:125850:27"/>
the Kings attroney, and by the Award of the Barrons in open Court, all manner of proceſſe, writts, Injunctions, and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoever, that be to be made on his ſide, beſides the ordinary proceſſe and writte of every Terme, whereof he likewiſe maketh ſtay, and <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> by War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and Award of the Barons as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p>He entreth Judgment, according as the Lord cheife Baron and Barons of the Court Commandeth him, of all Pleas dependingon his ſide both for the king and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, though the Kings learned Councell would willinglie have the Judgment goe otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>He entreth Judgement of his owne Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie by the Ancient Courſe of the Court of Pleas of Courſe, and whereof there are day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Preſidents which were not able otherwiſe to be overcome if they ſhould be read and followed openly in the Court.</p>
               <p>He ſendeth the red Book by one of his Clerkes with the fourth Baron moſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, and in his abſence, with the next Baron into the Kings Bench, and Common Pleas in the Terme time, to remove any
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:125850:28"/>
matter ſued there againſt any Officer, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, Servitor, or any of their men, or any Accomptant there, that prayeth his privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in time of any of the ſame Court, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ſaid red Booke ſhewed, and the parties ſoe teſtified by the Baron to be of the Court as aforeſaid, his Priviledge is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily allowed.</p>
               <p>He receiveth into his Office all the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates of the Subſides, Fifteens, &amp; Tenths, granted to the Prince by Parliament, and certifieth unto the Exchequer, whereupon he maketh his two Bookes called The States of Subſidies, and the State of Fiſteens, in which is entred the Collectors names, and for what places, with the ſumme totall of every Certificate, as they doe come in with their payments agreeable thereunto, ſoe are they troſſed and entred cleere, that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſtand open while the money is payed, and diſcharged.</p>
               <p>He ſendeth every Hillary and Trinitie T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, ſeverall parchment Bookes, to all the Cuſtomers, Controllers, Survaiors and Searchers of the Parts and Creekes through <hi>England,</hi> to make the firſt and ſecond halfe yeares Entries in the ſame of the Kinges
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:125850:28"/>
Majeſties Cuſtomes and Subſides, and the Cocketts thereof, according to certaine late orders in the late Queens time ſent unto them thereof. And likewiſe every <hi>Michel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> and <hi>Eaſter</hi> Terme he receiveth the ſame by the Oath again of the ſaid Officers in open Court, or before ſome one of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons out of the Court, that they have made all true Entries in the ſame, and as they ought to have done.</p>
               <p>He receiveth, from ſome one of the three Barons, and of the Auditors of the Court Attending on them, all Sheriff, forraign accounts, Collectors accounts of Subſidies and Fifteens, and the Cofferers accounts, which he taketh, &amp; the Accomptants name with his addition of account, and the ſumme totall and the debts of the ſame, and ſo putteth every of them ever by himſelfe, or one of the Clerks of his Office to the Treaſurors Remembrancers ſide to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred there in like ſort; both which Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers ſhould likewiſe receive all the great accounts taken now before the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Preſts and the Receivours and Miniſters accounts of the late Augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Revenue, taken before the Auditors of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:125850:29"/>
the Shires to make like Entries thereof in both their Offices, and to be conveyed in the viewes of every yeares Remembrance, and that he to whome it did appertaine, might make proceſſe upon the ſame, where any cauſe ſhould ſo fall out, and ſo noe <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> or debt thereupon, by that meanes ſhould be behind, and to be out of Proceſſe every Terme while they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged.</p>
               <p>He ſendeth commiſſion of <hi>Niſi prius</hi> by the kings Attorneys Warrant onely, upon tryall of any matters within his office at the Aſſizes in the countrie <hi>Adtenorem Recordi</hi> under the Exchequer Seale with it, But at the <hi>Niſi Prius</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> at Guildhall, he hath the very Record of his Office brought thither, and it is without commiſſion, becauſe my Lord cheife Baron ſitteth thereon, and the Kings Attorney and his Majeſties learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Councell either be, or appoint to be there for his Highneſſe.</p>
               <p>Hee hath other ſpeciall Authorities, preheminences, and matters, appointed to his Office by the Articles of the uniting of the ſaid Court of Augmentations to the Exchequer, which are referred thither for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:125850:29"/>
breifeneſs and for more certaintie at large of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Lord Treaſurors Remembrancer</head>
               <p>IS the ſecond Remembrancer of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer and belike of old time was ſo called, for that it was then in the Lord Treaſurors gift, or that he had ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſervice appointed to him by the Lord Treaſuror to remember him of, or to be kept in Record.</p>
               <p>He hath his Office cheifly eſtabliſhed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the execution of the originall, ſave for the great accounts, the Cuſtomers, control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and ſearchers, that is yearly ſtreated to him out of the Chancerie, and is otherwiſe called <hi>Extractus Cancellarioe,</hi> being the yearely ſtreate <hi>Verbatim,</hi> as they paſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> from time to time of all Sheriffs, and Eſcheators Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, of all Cuſtomers, Controllers, and Searchers Patents, of all Receivers, Reeves, Beadles, Bayliffs, Collectors, and Stewards
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:125850:30"/>
Pattents of all grants of lands, and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for life, in ſee ſimple, ſee taile gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or ſpeciall, of all denizonſhips, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Arch biſhops, and Biſhops, erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of any Abbies, Priories, Colledges, Chauntries, Hoſpitalls, Schooles, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, of all cuſtodies of any Honers Caſtles, Lordſhips, Mannors Chaces, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts. Parkes ſpeciall, and generall, after the Courſe of the Chancerie, &amp; ouſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, of all Licenſes of Alinations going over ſea, tranſportations, Introductions, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, imparkings, and Incloſures, of all pardons, Alienations, intruſions, treſpaſſes, utlegaries, felonies, murders, miſpriſions, treaſons, and forfeitures, of all reſtitutions of blood, goods, and Chattells, lands and Tenements, of all leaſes for Terme of life, or for yeares, of all Fines groſſe and ſmall, of all Writts of reſtitutions of Temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, of any Abbey, Priorie, Archbiſhopprick, wards and ſeized lands and Tenements, of all <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Cl. Extremum, Mandamus, Meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us inquirendum, et qu. plura.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He out of the ſaid Originall, maketh his Booke called the Roll of Proſſers, which is a record, and a part of the remembrance of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:125850:30"/>
every yeare of the comming of every Cro, <hi>Michalis,</hi> and Cro' <hi>Clauſ. paſch.</hi> into the receipt of all Sheriffs, Bayliffs, Farmers, Eſcheators, and men of certaine Townes within the realm, and of putting in a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their proffer made of the iſſues of their Offices, at which if any of the Sheriffs made default by himſelfe or their Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, or pay not into the receipt there by Tallie <hi>infra menſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi> following, they forfeit their recognizance, and the Bayliff, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and Eſcheators that come not then to appeare either by themſelves or their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torneys, are amerced at halfe their proffer, And if they pay not their proffer <hi>infra menſem</hi> following, then doe they looſe their proffer and pay it unto the receipt without having any Allowance of the ſame upon their account.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He</hi> when the ſaid proffers are done mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Proclamation in the receit before they ariſe That all Sheriffs, Bayliffs of liberties, and Eſcheators, do pay their proffers as they are accuſtomed <hi>infra menſem,</hi> and keepe their dayes of prefixion for their Accounts in the Exchequer according as by the Court
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:125850:31"/>
they are appointed upon paine and perill that ſhall fall thereof.</p>
               <p>Hee thereupon by his booke called the ſcroule of accounts made out of the Rolls of profers, and out of any other part of the yearly remembrance, called <hi>Dies datus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cecom, et Eſcaet. ad Computand. poſt profra</hi> every <hi>Michelmas</hi> Terme, doth call all Sheriffs, Bayliffs, and Eſcheators of the year laſt paſt to account, ſome <hi>Cr. Sc. Michis,</hi> ſome <hi>tres ſeptiman Sc. Micahis,</hi> ſome <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Micahis;</hi> ſome <hi>Cr. Simon et Jude,</hi> ſome <hi>Cr. annimarum,</hi> ſome <hi>Cr. Martini,</hi> ſome <hi>Octabis Hillarii,</hi> ſome <hi>Cr. Hillarii</hi> ſome <hi>Quinden. Hillarii,</hi> ſome <hi>Cr. Purific.</hi> and ſome <hi>Quinden. Paſ.</hi> as every of theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dayes of prefixion of ancient have been ſet by the Court, and as they thought they ſhould be able to overcome, and finiſh their Accounts.</p>
               <p>He out of the Originall of the Chancery the Roll of proffers, <hi>Dies dat. Viceom. &amp; Eſcaet.</hi> the ſcroule of Accountants, and other Records, both preceding and following thereupon, doth make a yearely Booke called the Roll of Writs, that is a part alſo of the yearly Remembrance made
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:125850:31"/>
in his Office, in which he enrolleth all <hi>Bria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>returnabil. de Term. Hillar. Paſcae ſectae Trinitatis, &amp; ſectae Michaelis,</hi> every year ſome from the Originall, ſome from all the parts of the yearely Remembrance that is made with him, ſome from the tranſcript of Offices, yearely ſtreated into his Office out of the Chancery, ſome from Offices found before the Eſcheator, <hi>Virtute officij,</hi> and certified to him from the debts of the Pipe, put in his booke called <hi>Nomine Eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et. &amp; ceduta Pipae,</hi> and ſome from the ſtreat of Common Pleas, called the Fynes.</p>
               <p>He out of the Originall from all Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Bayliffs, Reeves, Collectors, and Beadles Patents of any the Kings Lands or Tenements, doth inroll and write, <hi>Venire facias ad computand.</hi> or <hi>diſtringas ad red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend. compotum,</hi> from all grants of Honors, Caſtles, Lordſhips, Mannors, Lands, and Tenements granted by the Prince to any for life, in fee ſimple, fee taile generall or ſpeciall. he doth inroll and write <hi>Diſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas ad faciend fidelitatem &amp; ad faciend. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mag. &amp; fidelitatem,</hi> or a Writ of Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when the taile is ſpent, and otherwiſe as the caſe requireth, from all Denizen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:125850:32"/>
he maketh a <hi>Diſtring as ad faciend ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mag.</hi> from all cuſtodies of Lands and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, or Farmes, hee doth inroll and write, <hi>Diſtringas ad faciend, fidelitatem,</hi> or <hi>homag. &amp; fidelitatem,</hi> or <hi>ad reſpondend. de velevijs,</hi> from all pardons of Outlawries, Attainders, Felonies, Murders, Treaſons, Miſpriſions of Treaſons.</p>
               <p>He doth inroll and write <hi>Diſtringas ad reſpondend. de omnieo quod ad Regem perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, &amp;c. velcertiorari quae bona &amp; catalla A. B. habuit, &amp;c.</hi> From all licences of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienations, hee doth inroll and write, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringas ad faciend. fidelitatem,</hi> or <hi>ad audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end &amp; terminand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He doth inroll and write Writs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of any Temporalties.</p>
               <p>He doth inroll and write, <hi>Diſtringas ad reddend. comp. de exitibus temporal. &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Cercioraries,</hi> ſometimes, <hi>Quis rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit exitus et profit. temporal.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He from the ſayd Roll of proffers, doth inroll and write againſt ſuch as pay not their profers, <hi>Infra menſem.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>capias pro contemptu,</hi> with a <hi>Fierifacias pro proffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee</hi> from the ſayd ſcroule of Accounts
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:125850:32"/>
grounded upon <hi>Dies datus</hi> aforeſayd, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme againſt Sheriffs that make default at their days of prefixion, doth make a Record of five pounds for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day of payment, after hee makes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault while four dayes next be paſt, which is ſet down in the Pipe to be charged upon them, or is levied upon a <hi>Fierifacias</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Princes Letter come aforeſayd for the diſcharge of ſuch Amerciament, and then he doth inroll and write out an attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his Body, Goods, Chattells, Lands Tenements, while he cometh into account, and putteth in Bayle to end and finiſh the ſame, and againſt all Bayliffs of Liberties that make like default, hee enrolleth and writeth out like Attachment as hee did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt the Sheriffs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee</hi> from Commiſſions that is a part of the yearly Remembrance layd in his Office, and made by Warrant or commandement of the Court, or upon ſome other depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of Record, <hi>Ad inquirend. Ad faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. Ad Exequend. Ad perinplend. Ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiend.</hi> or <hi>Ad certificand.</hi> doth enroll pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and Writs out of the ſame againſt the Commiſſioners thereof, <hi>Ad liberand. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiones,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:125850:33"/>
ad certificand. ad comput and</hi> or <hi>alia faciend.</hi> as the matter offereth.</p>
               <p>He upon the <hi>Communia,</hi> that is the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Records of all the pleas put in every Terme within his Office, and another part of the ſayd yearly Remembrance, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll proceſſe, and doth write the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the partyes whom they concerne, <hi>Adfaciend. ſidelitatem homag. &amp; ſidelitatem magn. Serjantians, et parvam Serjantians, et ad reſpondend.</hi> &amp;c. as the ſeverall Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and judgements of the ſame doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
               <p>He even ſo doth inroll proceſſe and writ out of the ſame from all other parts and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of their Remembrance, and from all other Records riſing in his Office, are brought into the ſame of ſuch kind, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as the matter in them by the courſe in the Court doth require.</p>
               <p>He upon all theſe proceſſes that do thus iſſue out of his Office, doth admit every man to plead in diſcharge of any of them that hath cauſe, and matter, and by the courſe of the Court is bound thereunto, but no firſt Patent of Lands or Tenements, or he that ſueth a licenſe of alienation, or
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:125850:33"/>
a pardon of Alienation, or Livery ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or generall, or an <hi>Ouſterlemaine,</hi> or after the courſe of the Chancery, that is ſtreated as afore in the yearely originall is compelled or ſuffered to plead upon any ſuch firſt proceſſe inrolled upon the ſame, and written out by every of them are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to do their fealty, or to pay their fine for a reſpit of homage, at any Terme they come in after the ſame ſent forth, and ſo keeping ſtill the payment of the ſame Fine every fifth Terme, they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe made out againſt the ſame Land their fine is made for, but their fifth terme homage written to put them in Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the payment of their fine, while either they be returned dead, or <hi>Nihil ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet</hi> in the ſame Land.</p>
               <p>He upon all ſuch Returns of <hi>Mortuus,</hi> or <hi>Nihil habet</hi> from the Originall, or of like ſervice of Writs from pleas, or any other Record in his Office, doth ſtrait write out the next Term after ſuch Return, a <hi>Dic. te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents</hi> of the ſame Land, the Tenant is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned <hi>Mortuns eſt,</hi> or <hi>Nihil habet,</hi> &amp;c. for the anſwering of the which the party that is returned the now tenant of the ſaid
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:125850:34"/>
land, muſt ſhew he hath therefore a licence of Alienation, or a pardon of Alienation, or a livery generall, or ſpeciall, or an <hi>Ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterlemaine,</hi> or after the courſe of the Chancery by which he entred, and he muſt plead either the ſame or ſome generall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that will ſerve for his diſcharge, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, with the <hi>Nec non ad oſtendend.</hi> goeth current ſtill every Terme, while hee come in and plead as aforeſayd.</p>
               <p>He admitteth any ſuch perſon that hath any ſuch Land whereof the Tenant is retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Mortuns eſt,</hi> or <hi>Nihil habet</hi> before the <hi>Dic. Tenement.</hi> goeth forth thereof, with a <hi>Nec non ad oſtendend.</hi> upon the ſayd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to come into his Office, and inroll there his licence or pardon of Alienation of the ſame Land, and to ſhew his convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof, and likewiſe to enroll his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſpeciall &amp; generall, the <hi>Ouſterlemain,</hi> or after the courſe of the Chancery, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame enrollment, and ſhew he doth admit ſuch perſon to do his fealty, and to pay his Fine upon a Writ made from the ſayd enrollment, and ſhew of his eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to agree therewith, without any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pleading, becauſe all ſuch Writs be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:125850:34"/>
like the firſt writts inrolled from the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and written out as aforeſaid againſt the firſt tennant onely of the land by good matter of Record.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He</hi> upon all pleas put into his Office where the Kings Attorney may make an Averrment contrary to the plea of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and where the partie pleadeth anie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne matter then is of record in that Court, and allowed of, or would diſcharge any Claim, title, or Intereſt of the King by the ſame plea, ſave in the ſaid ordinarie Writts for fealtie and <hi>Homage</hi> ſealtie, and ſuch like, doth by himſelfe or ſome Clerk of his, make the Kings Attorney ever privy to all ſuch pleas, their replicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and rejoynders, who doth reſpect them and conſider them, and at length either doth confeſſe them, or referreth them, or giveth his Warrant out under his hand to have them tryed in the Countrie at the Aſſizes of <hi>Niſi prius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He</hi> according to the Ancient order of the Court, upon all other ordinarie Pleas exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by him with one of the Clerks of his office concerning Writts of ſervice, and ſuch like, doth enter Judgment alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:125850:35"/>
making the kings Attorney or the Court privie thereto, which ever in this wiſe were diſpatched as agreeable to the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He</hi> either upon the firſt writ from the originall. or upon the writts written from the ſaid Pleas, or upon diſtreſſes from the Streat of the fines of the Commiſſion pleas, or from writts upon ſuch like records in his office, doth ſet over perſons fines for reſpit of <hi>Homage</hi> payable every fifth Terme according to a rate given him by the Court at his firſt comeing into his office where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a record was then made, and is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>the Fines for reſpit of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, every fift Terme of lands and Tenements.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>s</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Three pounds <hi>per Annum</hi> downwards 0 4</item>
                        <item>Five pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> downwards 0 8</item>
                        <item>Sixe pounds thirteene ſhillings four pence <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> downwards 1 0</item>
                        <item>Ten pounds <hi>per annum</hi> downwards 1 8</item>
                        <item>Eighteene pounds <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi>
                           <pb n="65" facs="tcp:125850:35"/>
downwards 2 0</item>
                        <item>Twenty pounds <hi>per annum</hi> downwards 3 4</item>
                        <item>Thirty pounds <hi>per annum</hi> downwards 5 0</item>
                        <item>Forty pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> downwards 6 8</item>
                        <item>Sixty pounds <hi>per annum</hi> downwards 10 0</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>And noe ſuch fines are ſet higher but upon Noblemen which according to the greatneſs, or meaneſſe of their lands, are ſet ſome at thirteen ſhillings fourpence ſome at twentie ſhillings ſome twentieſix ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings eight pence ſome at thirtie ſhillings and ſome at forte ſhillings, to be payed every fifth Terme, and none above, nor ſo high but for Dukes.</p>
               <p>He hath ſet downe in his Book called <hi>nomina Vic.</hi> by the Clerk of the Pipe every yeare, the debts of all Sheriffs, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs of liberties, and men of certain Towns that are found, and caſt upon their accounts entred in the Pipe, and in another of his Bookes called <hi>Nomina Ecaetor,</hi> he hath every yeare the like debts of Eſcheators ſet
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:125850:36"/>
downe by the ſame Clerk of the Pipe; for all the which, he maketh Attachment and other ordinarie proceſſe of the Court for the levying of the ſame, as the caſe doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
               <p>He hath in a third Book in his Office called <hi>Schedula Pipe,</hi> All debts ſet downe by the Clark of the Pipe, of ſuch perſons as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the oppoſalls of the Sherift of their ſummons, be ſaid by them to be dead, to the end he ſhould make a <hi>Diem clauſit Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremum,</hi> after the death of ſuch debtors to the Sherift, which is the award of the Court, and of purpoſe to enquire what day and yeare they died, and what goods and Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells, and of what value they had at the day of their death, and to whoſe hands the ſame came, and now be, and to ſeize the ſame in whoſe hands ſoever they be, and to leavy the ſame debt, and have them before the Barons ſuch a day.</p>
               <p>And if their goods and Chattells be not ſufficient to pay the ſaid debt then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what lands and Tenements, and to what yearely value they had at the day of their deaths, or when they became debtors, or ever ſince, and to whoſe hands and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:125850:36"/>
the ſame came after their deceaſe and in whoſe hands they now be, and the ſame to ſeize in whoſe hands ſoever they be and keepe ſafe, and to Anſwere the iſſues and profits thereof untill the ſaid debt be fully ſatisfied and payed, or that he other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is Commanded, and to diſtraine all the Executors of the Teſtament of the ſaid debtors, as Adminiſtrators of the goods and Chattells that were his, and alſo the heires, and Ter Tenants of the ſame debtors, if they have not Executors to Anſwere the ſame debt, and all to the intent the ſame might this way be payed that could not by the ſummons of the Pipe be ſo levied. And likewiſe he hath put in his ſaid Booke of <hi>Schedula Pipe,</hi> by the Clerk of the Pipe, other great and ſpeciall debts that the Court will have ſpedeier and ſharper proceſſ made for them by the ſaid ſummons, to the intent the Debtors ſhould be either quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Attached and brought into the Court, or the money payed and Anſwered to the Sheriffs, or into the Reccit, as ſhould beſt fall out for the eaſe and diſpatch of the debtors.</p>
               <p>He taketh into his Office, all Streats of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:125850:37"/>
Fines, iſſues, and Amerciaments, ſent into the Court from the Kings Bench, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pleas, the Juſtices of Aſſize, and all Juſtices of the Peace, through <hi>England,</hi> which are by him delivered over by the Rolls of ſtreats into his Office to the Clark of the Streats to write out, who ſets his hand thereto for the Receipt of the ſame.</p>
               <p>He taketh on his ſide alſo (as the Kings Remembrancer doth afore) all Sheriffs for raigne accounts, Bayliffs accounts, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheators accounts, Cuſtomers accounts, Collectors accounts, of Subſidies and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teens, and the Cofferers accounts (as before is declared) in the point amongſt the matters of the Kings Remembrancers ſide.</p>
               <p>He ruleth the ordinary petitions that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſayd Accountants do make or pray upon their ſayd accounts to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them without the privity of the Court, being matter of Record and Preſident in Court for the diſcharge of the ſame, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their new and firſt petitions, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed from time to time by the Judgement of the Court, and ſo he ruleth them under his hand accordingly, and there entred ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:125850:37"/>
in the <hi>Venos</hi> or the poſtſcript of the yeares, wherein they ſhould lye, that be part of the Remembrance for that year.</p>
               <p>Hee by the Lord Treaſurers Warrant, the Chancellors Warrant, the Vice-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers Warrant, the Lord chiefe Barons Warrant, the Kings Attorneyes Warrant, out of the Court, and in the Court by the Order of the Barons, doth make all manner of proceſſe, Writs, Commiſſions, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions for matters on his ſide, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſtayes, and <hi>Superſede as</hi> of them, as he is by them willed and commanded.</p>
               <p>He writeth once a year the iſſues of his Office returned by the Sheriff every Term, and laſt upon all manner of diſtreſſes in the ſame, which being bound up and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Clerks of his Office, are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over by the Roll of Eſtreates to the Clerke of ſtreats to write out, who ſetteth his hand to the ſayd Roll for recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Hee layeth every Lent yearly a Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the 5 year before, &amp; dothregiſter &amp; make up cleere all the Records of the ſame, or diſcontinueth them that cannot be made perfect, and inrolleth proceſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:125850:38"/>
of thoſe matters, and ſo receiveth the ſame by new writing them out againe. In which time alſo of Lent, he entreth alſo eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Writ in that Roll of Writs of that yeares Remembrance that is Law, and all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage Writs of the ſame, and likewiſe all the fylances of his Office of every Terme ſince that Remembrance, then he doth lay to ſee if they all be ſtill currant in courſe and every Term as they ought to be, and ſuch as are found wanting by falling off, or otherwiſe, are then new enrolled in the Roll of Writs, of that year, and ſo are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and ſet current anew, that the leaſt Writ of his Office, whereby the King is to have any right or profit is not ſuffered to be loſt, nor yet left to be uncurrent.</p>
               <p>He hath other ſpeciall Anthorityes, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignments, and matters appointed to his Office by the Articles of the uniting of the late Court of augmentations to the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, which are referred thither for breif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and for more certainty at large of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:125850:38"/>
               <head>Sheriffs Accounts.</head>
               <p>HE, if the Sheriffs do account by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, and have no tally of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward after the Secondary hath caſt up eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sheriffs firſt ſumm, doth examine it; and ſeeth that the ſame be made only of Sheriffs vicommells, upon which hee giveth him allowance, firſt of his profers payed by tally, and then of all ſuch allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, as are given him by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Then after his ſaid Secondary hath made up the Sheriffs ſecond ſumm upon his <hi>De debitis plurimum,</hi> which be his <hi>Tots</hi> and upon his <hi>De pluribus debit is</hi> charge which be his greene Wax, and his whole as before, or ſo many of them as he is charged with, hee cauſeth the Sheriffs forraigne accounts to be caſt up, and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth firſt to the ſame ſecond ſumm, the old ſeizures thereof, which be Lands and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſeized before by his predeceſſors, upon the proceſſe of the Court, and then chargeth the Sheriffs own ſeizures to the ſame, which be of lands &amp; Tenements ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:125850:39"/>
in his own time by Proceſs of the Court, &amp; ſo addeth to theſe ſuch Fellons goods as he hath ſeized himſelfe, After which things done, he giveth him allowance of all his payments, deductions, annuall Charges, and ſoe bringeth the <hi>Quietus eſt:</hi> And if the Sheriff do not account by Improvement but hath a Tally of reward, then the ſaid Secundary doth make up but one ſumme to ſuch Sheriff of his whole Charge afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Eſcheators Account</head>
               <p>HE conveyeth yearly into the great Roll breifly, the Eſcheators accounts of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sheire into the pipe of the ſame Shire where he is Eſcheator, he entreth the ſame and maketh his allowance both of his prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers and of all his petitions he maketh in the Treaſurors Remembrancers office, in diſcharge of his debt, and ſoe is the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheator brought downe alſo to <hi>Quietus eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:125850:39"/>
               <head>Roll of Accounts</head>
               <p>HE doth every Lent make up a great Roll of all the ſaid accounts, as the Kings and Treaſurors Remembrancers doe lay every lent a Remembrance in either of their Offices, and ſuch debts and Remains as be not, or cannot be made quit and cleare in the ſaid great Roll made up every Lent, are Conveyed into the Pipe of the great Roll that ſhould be made up for the year following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Customers Accounts</head>
               <p>HE hath for all the Cuſtomers accounts yearly a Book called the Cuſtomers Roll into which every Cuſtomers Charge and Allowance is Conveyed yearely and the debts and the remaines in them are from thence conveyed over from time to time in the great Roll, and are ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out, or Written for the proceſſe from <hi>Schedula Pipa,</hi> where they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:125850:40"/>
alſo to be the ground of the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Remembrancer to make the proceſſe by.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Rolls of Subſidies and Fifteenes</head>
               <p>HE hath even ſo ſpeciall Rolls for all ſuch Subſidies and Fifteenes granted to the Prince by act of Parliament, called the Subſidie Roll of the Clergie, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie Roll of the Laity, and the Roll of Fifteens of ſuch a king, or of two or three Kings together as it falleth out, or may be continued, Into which he entreth the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall accounts of the ſeverall Collectors, and of ſuch debts as remaine unpayed upon anie of them, are conveied likewiſe into the great Roll, moſt meete for the ſame to be Charged in, and ſo are ſummoned out alſo, or written for by proceſſe from <hi>Schedula Pipe,</hi> by the Treaſurors Remembrancer as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:125850:40"/>
               <head>Rolls of the Wardrobe and Coffers</head>
               <p>HE hath likewiſe a ſpeciall Roll for the Wardrobe and Coffers accounts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether called <hi>Magna Guardrobe Roll,</hi> and the cofferers Roll, into which their accounts are ingroſſed, and the debts in the ſame are Conveied over as afore into the great Roll, ſave that the Cofferers yearly Remaine ſtandeth ſtill into his next years accounts do paſſe to be examined and Charged, and ſo is ſtill on from yeare to yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Rotulus examinatus</head>
               <p>HE is an Officer that maketh a yearly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in his Office of all the Ancient Revenues in the Exchequer that was there before the uniting of the late Court of aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations and the firſt fruit and Tenthes to the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:125850:41"/>
He putteth in Charge yearly into his Book called the great Roll, all Sheriffs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts Eſcheators accounts, Bayliffs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and men of certaine Townes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts that are called to account by the Treaſurors Remembrancer.</p>
               <p>He maketh therein the Charge of the ſaid accounts for the Counties, Cities, and Townes of the Realme, as they be and lie in the order of letters by the Alphabet, end ſo the firſt Pipe thereof beginneth with the Charge of the Sheriffs of <hi>Bedford,</hi> and <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and Townes as it falleth out by order of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>He maketh the firſt Charge of every Sheriffe to be his vicommells, which be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſecond titles <hi>Poſt tras dat. et Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic: comitat:</hi> as they call them. The firſt whereof ſeemeth to be lands and Tenements in the Conquerors hands after he had given away aſmuch as pleaſed him at his Entrie. The ſecond ſeemes to be thoſe lands, tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Rents, ſervices, and profitts which came to the Crowne afterwards by Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Forfeitures, and ſeizures, moſt of which where they be are not known to the Sheriffs
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:125850:41"/>
of the Realme, but yet many of them are gathered up in rents by their Bayliffs, as knowne to them by tradition and ſucceſſion and ſo are either payed or made up by them to ſo much as he is charged with yearly in the Pipe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Farme Rents and ſervices.</head>
               <p>HE after this, doth Charge him with the Fee farme Rents and ſervices of the ſhire, but are reſerved there, and drawne downe into the great Roll out of the yearly originall of the Chancerie ſtreated as afore into the Treaſurors <hi>Remembrancers</hi> office, which Clerk of the Pipes Secondarie is bound from time to time, and from <hi>Roll</hi> to <hi>Roll</hi> to peruſe, and finding in the ſame any yearly <hi>Revenue, Reſervation,</hi> profit, <hi>Remainder</hi> or <hi>Revertions</hi> reſerved to the Crowne, he draweth them downe into the great <hi>Roll,</hi> and maketh Charge thereof in the Shire where they be, ſo as ever after where they be payable, they be yearly ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:125850:42"/>
out before by the Controller of the Pipe to the Sheriff of that Countie. And all the ſaid <hi>Remaines</hi> and <hi>Reverſions,</hi> are conveyed into the <hi>Roll</hi> of the <hi>Reverſions,</hi> that is another Book in the Pipe, and made from time to time, that when any of them do revert a gain into the Crowne, are to be put into <hi>Schedula Pi.</hi> that is mentioned, before the Treaſurors <hi>Remembrancer</hi> make out the Writ of <hi>Reverſion</hi> to enquire thereof; and to ſeize the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Oblata or old Debts</head>
               <p>HE maketh <hi>oblata</hi> the next title of the Charge of the Sheriff, with the old debts brought as it were together from precedent yeares, and be written from other <hi>Rolls</hi> to the Sheriffs of that yeare, and after that title, he ſetteth to his Charge <hi>Nova oblata,</hi> which be as it were new debts brought together, and drawne downe from Cuſtomers accounts, or Eſcheators accounts, or recovered and ſet downe from ſome one of the <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:125850:42"/>
ſides, or other <hi>Records</hi> or grounds of the Court, and have their names belike of <hi>Oblata</hi> upon the ſame that are ſo brought together.</p>
               <p>He after the forraine Oppoſer hath made up the ſcroule, and ſumme of the greene wax of every Sheriff in the ſeverall titles the ſame doth ariſe, and it is delivered into the Pipe, doth make up the next Charge of the Sheriff <hi>Viridi Cera,</hi> which riſeth out of the ſtreats of the Fines, iſſues, and Amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaments that came from the Kings Bench, the Common pleas, the Juſtice of the Peace, the King, or Treaſurors Remembrancers ſide.</p>
               <p>He ſtraight after this, doth Charge every Sheriff with his Caſualties, which are all manner of Debts of Caſualties, and Releifes, Fines, Amerciaments upon the Sheriffs, debts recovered and ſuch like as are drawne downe either from anie Record of anie of the Remembrancers of the Eſchequer, or from anie other ground, matter or ſeizure of the Court, and be ſo brought toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>And the Sheriff Anſwereth as he hath Cauſe to every ſumme, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch a ſumme
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:125850:43"/>
within liberties, and ſheweth whoſe they be Then the forraine Oppoſer ſetteth againſt that ſumme, the name of the Owner of the liberties, and if he have the ſame in Claime by Ancient Preſident either knowne or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified to the ſorraine Oppoſor out of the Pipe, he giveth the Bayliffs of the liberties allowance thereof, and maketh <hi>Clamen</hi> in the margent in the originall Record againſt the ſumme, otherwiſe he maketh ſpeciall <hi>tot.</hi> againſt the ſame ſumme thus: or or: in which pricks, and by which pricks of uſe, he knoweth whoſe liberties the ſame pricks do meane, Then the Sheriff going on, and ſaying to another ſum <hi>tot.</hi> the forraine Oppoſor marketh it in the margent in the originall thus without pricks, and ſo that is a Charge to the Sheriff onely And after the Sheriff ſaying to another <hi>Summa nihil,</hi> the forraine oppoſor doth marke alſo againſt the <hi>Summa</hi> in the Margent in <hi>Rottulo.</hi> 21, or 13 as the Streate is of the yeare of the King Whereof the oppoſall is. and he goeth through that originall record, his whole libertie of the reſt of the Sheriffs greene wax ſtreated unto him, and marketh every ſumme in ſuch wiſe as before.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:125850:43"/>
He afterwards maketh the Sheriffs ſcronle in parchment of all the totalls, with pricks, &amp; caſteth up the ſeverall totall ſums if they be in ſeverali natures, &amp; where any Δ' with pricks is wthin any ſuch totall ſums, as for example, <hi>A. B. Vicecom. pred. oneratur minit. exitus</hi> twenty pounds to pull off the 'Δ, with pricks from the Sheriff, he ſaith immediately after, that totall <hi>Summa C. qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus C. D. ball. libertat. C. F. venit per G. H. Attorn. ſuum et V. inde 51. et ſic debit,</hi> fifteen pounds, and ſo every Bayliff from the ſaid ſcroule is charged in the great Roll, with the 'Δ, with pricks where it concerns, and the other without pricks is charged in the ſame Roll to the Sheriff himſelfe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>He ſaith that he leaveth the <hi>Nihils</hi> that be marked in the Margent of the Originall Record in <hi>Rotulo</hi> 12. or 13. as aforeſayd, for the Clarke of the <hi>Nihils</hi> to write out by his ſayd markes in <hi>R</hi> when they be delivered againe into the Clerke of the Streats Office.</p>
               <p>He alloweth to the Sheriffs the Juſtices of Peace wages of his Shire out of the Fines and Forfeitures before the Juſtices of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:125850:44"/>
peace thereof if the Streat will bear them, layed out before the Sheriffs for the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wages, according to the Statute, of the which allowance, and of the particular names of the Juſtices, the ſayd forraigne oppoſer doth deliver a Roll into the Pipe for the Clarke of the Pipes Warrant to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſame wages to the Sheriff.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Clarke of the Streats.</head>
               <p>IS the Officer that receiveth yearely out of the Treaſurers Remembrancers Office, all the Streats of the Kings Bench, the Common pleas, the Juſtices of Aſſize, the Juſtices of the Peace, the Kings Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers ſide, his hand from time to time made in the ſayd Roll of the Streats, there reſtifying the receiving of the ſame.</p>
               <p>He writeh out yearly all the ſayd Streats to every Sheriff of <hi>England,</hi> as they in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſhire at the two <hi>Liberates</hi> of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, that be every <hi>Hillary</hi> Terme and <hi>Trinity</hi> Term, for to levy and to anſwer all the ſumms of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Hee maketh Schedules in parchment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:125850:44"/>
his hand agreeable with his Streats, ſent out as before with the ſumms of the ſame truly totalled, when any Sheriff will make petition to be diſcharged of any ſum in the ſame by good matter offered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Auditors of the Preſts</head>
               <p>BE they that take the old great accounts of the Exchequer, as <hi>Ireland, Barwick,</hi> the Mynt, the Loan, the Wars, the Ships, the Proviſions, the Hamper, the Ordnance the Clerk of the Works, and ſuch like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred before, who now declared the ſame before the Lord Treaſurer, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor and under Treaſurer only, and be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver entred in the Court of Exchequer, nor examined nor written upon there as they had wont to be.</p>
               <p>That upon many years ſo moving out, and writing proceſſe forth, ſound meerly deſperate and illeviable upon the parties, that owe them, either alive or being dead, upon their heirs, Executors, Adminiſtrators, their Goods, Chattells, Lands, Tenements or Ter Tenants, which deſperate debts of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:125850:45"/>
theirs that be alive, be by and by conveyed back again into the great Roll, and ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of the Chancery, afterwards to be ſufficient to anſwer either the whole, or ſome part of the debt.</p>
               <p>They have other ſpeciall Authorityes, Aſſigments, and matters appointed to this Office, by the Articles of the uniting of the late Court of Augmentations to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, which are referred thither for breifneſſe, and for more certainty at large of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Remembrancer of the firſt Fruits and Tenths.</head>
               <p>HAth his Office wholy eſtabliſhed by Articles of the unyting of the late Court of the fiſt Fruits and Tenths, unto the Exchequer, and by a late decree of our Court, concerning the altering thereof from the firſt erection, which for breifne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> here are referred over to the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:125850:45"/>
               <head>The Comptroller of the Pipe.</head>
               <p>IS an Office that was firſt deviſed to keep a Controll of the Pipe, that ſhould write and keep every year a like great Roll in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very matter of charge and diſcharge, as the Clark of the pipe doth, and ſhould lay every Lent ſuch a one, as well as he, but (as I learn) no ſuch Roll hath been made up by him for many years, and yet (as I hear) he writeth yearly now all the pipes of the great Roll, the Clerk of the Pipe doth keep, but he doth not yearly make them up into a great Roll.</p>
               <p>He only writeth out twice a year the two ſummons of every ſhire of the Realm <hi>viz.</hi> his firſt ſumuons every <hi>Hillary</hi> term, where in he writeth only the Sheriffs <hi>Vicondeles,</hi> his fee farmes, and ſometimes his <hi>Oblata,</hi> and likewiſe the ſecond ſummons every <hi>Trinity</hi> Terme, wherein hee writeth his <hi>Nova oblata,</hi> and caſualties, and ſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the oppoſalls of every Sheriff, he may if
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:125850:46"/>
he liſt ſee how every of them do <hi>O. Ni.</hi> or <hi>rot.</hi> every Terme of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Clerk of the Pleas.</head>
               <p>IS the Officer in whoſe Office, all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Court of the Exchequer, their Clerks and ſervants, all the Kings Majeſties Tenants and Farmers of any of his Lands, and Tenements, and all manner of accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Court of the Exchequer, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of their bar, ſo ſhould be ſued in, or may implead another, or any ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in any Action upon the caſe, or of treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, debt, <hi>De Ejectione firmoe,</hi> of <hi>Detinue,</hi> or ſuch like, as are ſued in the Kings Bench,</p>
               <p>He hath every ſuit proſecuted in his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice between party and party, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of any Court at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> by the red book, or out of any Court of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord elſewhere in <hi>England,</hi> by any Writ of proviledge for any of the ſaid perſons that are priviledged as before to ſue and to be ſued only there in the ſaid actions and no where elſe, if they will in time claim and ſue their priviledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:125850:46"/>
He in his Office bringeth all matters to an end, and either upon <hi>Nihil dicit</hi> or by Demurrers argued, or by verdict tryed in Court or by <hi>Niſi prius</hi> at the <hi>Gaild Hall</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> or at the Aſſizes in the County be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Juſtices of Aſſize, and ſo by the Judgment given upon every of the ſame, whereupon the party with whom Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is given for his Execution, hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the party condemned a <hi>Capias,</hi> an <hi>Alias,</hi> or <hi>Plures,</hi> and <hi>Fieri facias.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Forraigne Appoſer</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IS</hi> an Officer to whom all ſheriffs after they are appoſed of their ſummes out of the Pipe, do repair to be appoſed by him of their green wax, who appointeth them a day certein for the ſame, and ſo the ſheriff payes for the Clark of the ſtreats againſt that day to bring to <hi>Westminſter,</hi> the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Bookes and Records of their greene Wax.</p>
               <p>He at the day of the ſayd appoſall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, taketh the ſheriffs ſtreats, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Clark to look upon it, and he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:125850:47"/>
readeth the Origin all Record, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the Sheriff, what he ſaith to every ſumm therein, and the Clark ſeeth the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs ſtreats, if the Originall do agree with the Wax.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Kings Attorney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</head>
               <p>HE is made privy to all the Anſwers put in upon the ſayd nformations, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demurreth thereupon, or replyeth as he will, to bring the matter to an iſſue, and at his pleaſure to the King, all advantages of pleading, given to his highneſs by the Defendant, and ſometimes preſſeth the Court to hold and keep ſtill the ſame, and otherwiſe he yeildeth and ſuffereth the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to amend his plea, anſwer, and Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſo proceedeth to the joyning of an iſſue.</p>
               <p>He is made privy to all Replications drawn from the Kings ſide, and altereth and amendeth the ſame after his own liking and ſo is he likewiſe to the partyes Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:125850:47"/>
againſt the King, and either confeſſeth the plea, or the party Defendant, upon the ſame, either ſuffereth it to come to a try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by Jury at the Bar, or by <hi>Niſi prius</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> or in the County where the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lyeth, and ſo come all matters of plea to judgment, and an end, either upon the Kings Attorneyes confeſſion, or by tryall of Verdict, or by Demurrer, or by Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Court alone, or upon a <hi>Nihil dicit</hi> by the Kings Attorney.</p>
               <p>He in ſome caſes will not confeſs the plea for the party riſing upon the proceſſe of the Court, though it were reaſonable he ſhould without the Kings Majeſties War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, as when the party ſhould have his Right by way of Petition to the Prince, or that there is ſome Colour for him though not evident Right to ſtand againſt the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the Prince, and ſo refers him to the Court.</p>
               <p>He maintaineth his Informations, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, the Kings Right and proceſs of the Court, againſt all Counſellors, ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Witneſſes at the Bar, both in the Court, and in the Exchequer Chamber for the party, and upon the opening and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:125850:48"/>
of the Law, he either offereth the Defendant an iſſue, or to demur in Law with him upon the point, and ſo prayeth the Court he may do, and that the party may be inforced according to the Law to joyn iſſue, or demur in Law with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant as he thinketh will ſerve beſt for the Kings Title.</p>
               <p>He oftentimes, when the iſſue upon the Plea comes to tryall by the Jury, and that they are ſuſpected, or ſeem laboured doth ſometimes by exception quaſh the whole Jury, or ſo many of them as the matter cannot proceed to tryall, and ſometimes fearing the partiality of the whole pannell and ſuborned Witneſſes, he bringeth the matter to a Demurrer in Law upon the opening of the Evidence, and ſo ſaveth the Kings caſe politickly.</p>
               <p>He deviſeth all the Aſſurances the Kings Majeſty hath of any Lands and Tenements either ſold to his Highneſs for any debt, or aſſured unto his Majeſty for any debt to be payd at dayes, or elſe to be forfeited, which Indentures, Deeds, Fines, Recoveries, and other ſuch Writings, he delivereth now into the Kings Remembrancers Office that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:125850:48"/>
were wont to be kept in the Treaſury to be put in charge before the Auditors of the Counties, where the ſame Lands and Tenements do lye according to the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p>He ſuffereth ſometimes the Informers upon popular Actions, to put in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in their own name, when it is better the party Defendant be ſo proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or that he is of ſome fort an acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſo more meet that way to be ſued.</p>
               <p>He commandeth all the <hi>Remembrancers</hi> that there be no proceedings in certain matters depending in their Office, when he thinketh it beſt for the King, and Copies and Books to be made thereof, both for the judges, the Barons, and the Kings learned Counſell, as the caſe ſhall fall out.</p>
               <p>He ſuffereth ſometimes the Demurrers for the King to be argued, by other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Counſell, then the King retains by the party that followeth the Kings ſuit or his Tenant, or for his commodity, or for ſome other reſpect,</p>
               <p>He ſuffereth ſo the partyes ſometimes that folow the ſuite for the King, to bring
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:125850:49"/>
other Counſell to the Bar then the Kings, to open, plead, and defend the Kings Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle when he is in Court, and guideth them for the King.</p>
               <p>He maketh Warrants to all the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers to make all manner of Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Proceſſe, writs and Injunctions, as the Lord Treaſurer, the Chancellor, the Vice-Treaſurer, and the Lord Cheife Baron doth.</p>
               <p>He, when he underſtandeth, or is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained unto, that any ſtay, lingring, or <hi>Superſedeas</hi> is of any proceſſe or execution for the King, doth call ſtraight upon the Officers where it lyeth, and asketh why ſuch a proceſſe or matter ſtayeth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed of the cauſe, and it is by the Lord Treaſurers, Maſter Chancellor, Vice-Treaſurer, or the Courts order, he ſaith, ſtay them for a time, and I will move in it, but otherwiſe the matter proceedeth by his order with all expedition.</p>
               <p>He very ſeldom, or never of himſelf ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any proceſs matter or cauſe of the King but being moved there of by the cheif Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Court, he will ſeem for a time content, and leaveth the ſame to their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:125850:49"/>
yet he is content to give all ſuitors dayes to appear to ſhew their <hi>Rights,</hi> and bring in their Anſwers, Rejoynders, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, Evidences, and Patents.</p>
               <p>He with the Lord cheife Baron and the Court <hi>Pro miſis parcandis,</hi> doth ſet Fines for Compoſitions upon any Information depending in the Court by any ſpeciall Statute, and thereupon the partie defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant is diſcharged, and the record made up to ſhew how he hath Compounded, And ſo is drawne and ſet downe from the Roll of the Kings Remembrancers ſide and is charged and diſcharged in the Pipe as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <p>He certifieth into the Clerke of the Streate office yearly in the Exchequer, all the Kings moities recovered, and fines for Impoſitions made in the Kings Bench upon all penall ſummes or penall Statutes, and pay the ſame yearly into the Receipt by taile, and being ſet downe into the Pipe by the Clerke of the Streate, he hath his <hi>Quiet us eſt,</hi> for the ſame</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:125850:50"/>
               <head>The Kings Sollicitor</head>
               <p>SItteth next to the Kings Attorney in place, &amp; ſometimes Anſwereth the Barr, or the Court on the Kings behalfe, both in the abſence of the Kings Attorney, and when he is preſent, but otherwiſe he med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not any way with the Kings Attorneys office.</p>
               <p>He ceuſidereth with the Kings Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney all the Kings Majeſties hard and doubtfull caſes depending in Court, and ſheweth his opinion of the ſame both in Court and out of Court in the Exchequer Chamber.</p>
               <p>He waiteth on the Judges to know when they ſhall be able to Attend the Kings Cauſes that he and the Kings Attorney hath for matters depending in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer to informe them of, and both giveth every of them the caſe, and the Copies of all Books and Preſideats concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p>He argueth before the Kings Attorney all the Demurres that be in the Court for
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:125850:50"/>
the King, and ſometimes alone without the Attorney with other learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell out of the Kings fee, that are retian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him on the Kings ſide by the partie that followeth the ſuite for the King.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Auditors of the Exchequer</head>
               <p>BE they, That before the late united Courts to the Exchequer, did take and make all the accounts of the Ancient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue there, and now they take alſo the accounts of the receivers of the late Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation Revenue, as was allotted to every of them at the firſt coming thereof into one Court, and of the Miniſters of the ſame.</p>
               <p>They never take accounts of any Sheriff, Eſcheator, cuſtomer, Collector of Subſidies, or Fifteens, or the cofferers accounts, but by Aſſignement in open Court by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, and ſo entred in his Book, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent no accomptant ſhall ſeeke an Auditor of his Choice.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:125850:51"/>
They waite on ſome of the three youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Barons with every ſuch account when it is ingroſſed who examineth the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and the totalls of the ſame, and ſeeth if then the ſame account be ſtraight and true, and then it is ſet upon the head of ſuch Account examined, to know by whom it paſſed thus, or as it falleth out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>AB: Auditor CD: Clericus</head>
               <p>AND ſo it is deliveered by the Baron or Anditor firſt into the Kings Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers Office, and ſo from time to time to the Lord Treaſurors Remembrancers Office and ſo from him to the Clerke of the Pipes Office to be entred as aforeſaid in the Roll as it ſhould be after his nature as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p>They caſt out all Sheriffs in open Court, <hi>viz.</hi> two or three of them lay the ſummes and charge of their accounts as they be read to them in open Court by the Clerke
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:125850:51"/>
of the Pipe, and then they allow out of the ſame, their Annuall Deductions, and ſuch petitions as they make and be, read them in ſummes in open Court, and ſo try them either <hi>Aeque,</hi> or ſurpluſage, and if both or all the Auditors caſting doe agree, then be the Sheriffs delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the Court by Proclamation of ſome one of the Uſhers.</p>
               <p>They ride every <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme to their <hi>Audite,</hi> kept at the Kings Court in every ſhire as they are allotted eſpecially unto them, where they take the Miniſters accounts of the late Augumentation Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, at places certaine appointed before by their precept, and ſent out to the Bayliffs, Reeves, Collectors <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and there by order from my Lord Treaſuror, Maſter Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and the Vice-treaſuror, they have Authoritie to give certaine Allowances of reparations not exceeding the ſumme of where the kings is no bound thereunto and to do the ordinary things of their <hi>Audit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They make a breife declaration of every of their Receivers accounts every Lent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Lord Treaſuror, maſter Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:125850:52"/>
and Vice-treaſuror, and ſhew their laſt yeares Arrerages, and what every of them have payed in liverie money as in debt upon the ſame. He is then ordered to pay into the Receipt according to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute upon the determination of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, or is reſpited by the ſaid cheife, Officers, as they ſee cauſe for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Receivers</head>
               <p>BE onely of the late Augumentation Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue united of late unto the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer who receive by Statute of all tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the Rents reſerved upon any the ſaid late lands and likewiſe the Rents of the Farmers and all ſuch moneys as the Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Recyes, Bayliffs, Miniſters of the ſaid Revenue, do gather up within their <hi>Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule</hi> receits as either payable halfe yearly or found due upon account.</p>
               <p>They pay all Pentions within every of their receits, and are bound to pay all their money found due upon the determination of their accounts according to the Statutes in that hehalfe made, or they forefeit their
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:125850:52"/>
office, and they and their <hi>Sureties</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended beſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Surveyours</head>
               <p>BE onely of the ſaid Augmentation <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues</hi> and now are commonly put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Commiſſion for the king that go into theſe Shires where their Offices do lie, and beſides, are ordinarily appointed (if they have any skill) to ſurvey ſuch Mannors lands, and Tenements, as the Court hath occaſion, and doth think meete from time to time for any cauſe to be ſurvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Attorneys and Clerks of the Kings Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers Office.</head>
               <p>ALL thoſe that are conmmonly retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the parties in all ſuits and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Office to appeare and Anſwer
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:125850:53"/>
the Court for them and to follow all things in Court belonging thereto, but yet in ſuch order, that according to their Oath they do nothing uncomely, or ſecretly, in perjudice of the kings Majeſties right, and title, but that which is orderly, uſuall, and juſtifiable in open Court, and beſides every of them doth from time to time that which belongeth to his place and ſenioritie in the Office aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Attorneys and Clerks of the Pipe</head>
               <p>HAve aſſigned unto them and every of them ſpeciall, certaine Shires of the Realme by the order of their Office, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to every of their Seniorities, to the which every of them are toward, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to all the Accomptants of their owne Shires, and to every matter in the ſame, whereby one of them medleth not with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers Shires but every one of them are retained for the Clyents diſcharge and to bring every of them his <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> but
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:125850:53"/>
yet as he doth nothing uncomely or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly to hinder the Kings right, and then beſides, every of them doth in the Office what to his place Anciently apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Attorneys and Clarkes of the Clarks of the Pleas Office</head>
               <p>BE they that be retained betweene partie and partie in all ſuits commenced or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending there, who are in all orderly wiſe to follow their Clyents Cauſes, and to make their Pleas, Anſwers, Replications, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynders upon the ſame for learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to Conſider, and to do nothing therein but what is lawfull, comely and uſuall in the Court, and every of them doth beſides that as belongeth to their place in the ſame Office.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:125850:54"/>
               <head>The joyners of the tallies</head>
               <p>BE the ſecond Deputies of the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines for that purpoſe, and are ſworne at their Admittance to ſerve truly, who from time to time receive out of the receit the Foiles of all Tallies ſtricken there for any manner of perſon, and file them ſtraight upon a ſtring, which ſo filed, are kept under both their keys in their Cheſts, and when anie man bringeth any ſtock of thoſe to be joyned that muſt be firſt done, ere they can be allowed in the Pipe.</p>
               <p>The ſaid two Joyners ſeek ſtraight out the file of the ſame where it is filed, and taking it off, do ſee if the ſtock and the file do agree in hand, letter, and joyning, and be without ſuſpition, and then do they prick them both uſually with ſuch markes with their marking Iron, as uſually ſheweth the ſtock to be joyned then with the ſame tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and the day of the joyning thereof is entred in a Book with the letter and ſumme thereof, and afterwards that tallie ie filed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new in the Terme, that it is joyned and ſo
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:125850:54"/>
kept, And then one of the ſaid two Joyners delivereth over the ſtock that is joyned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Office of the Pipe, and that partie never handleth it after, and ſo it cometh to allowance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The two parcell makers</head>
               <p>BE the Officers that gather out, and make the parcells of all the Eſcheators ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts and be appointed to receive under their hands out of the Treaſurors Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers office ſett downe in the Roll of Streats there, all Tranſcripts of Offices ſent yearly thither out of the Chancerie that be found by anie Eſcheator through the Realme,</p>
               <p>Then they are to make the parcells of any Eſcheators accounts in any ſhire, they do call for the precedent account of the Eſcheator that was the yeare before of that Shire, out of which they gather firſt the parcells <hi>Veterum Eſcaetorum,</hi> that were in the ſaid laſt yeares account, and continued ſtill undiſcharged, and ſet them downe in long Rolls of parchment of fullneſs of letter,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:125850:55"/>
yearly value, tenure, and ſtate, as they be in the precedent account, and came from the Office out of which they were drawne firſt, then they gather the parcells of the new Eſcheators owne Offices he found in his time, and ſet them downe in the ſame Roll in like fullneſſe of letter, yearly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, tenure, and State, as they appeare in the ſame offices, which roll is incituled thus, Particular account <hi>A. B. Eſcaetor Com. Canc. &amp; Middleſex &amp;c.</hi> from ſuch a day <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And then in the margent of the Roll where the parcells do begin, there is <hi>Veterum Eſcaetorum,</hi> and ſo be theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells ſtill Conveied downe, and being ended, then is ſett in the margent of the Roll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>Nova Eſcaet.</hi> againſt the firſt parcell, beginning with, going downe, and ended, there is ſett in the margent of the ſame roll, <hi>Ter. &amp; tenem. &amp; catal. attinct. utlegat. fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. &amp; fugitivors.</hi> whereof the parcells be conveied if there be any, but commonly is ſet againſt that title eleven pound and they be <hi>Veter. Eſcaet. &amp; nova Eſcaet:</hi> totalled up by themſelves by the parcell-makers, which be the whole Charge of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheator, And they delivered thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:125850:55"/>
ſo ſummed up to the Auditor to whome ſuch Eſcheator is aſſigned, and by the Marſhall; and he <hi>Verbatim,</hi> accordingly doth ingroſſe up his account, which paſſeth further on in the Court, as before is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Clerk of the Nichills</head>
               <p>IS the Officer that repaireth to the Clerk of the Eſtreate every year, and ſeeth what Nihills be marked in <hi>Rottulo,</hi> in the whole <hi>Liberate,</hi> of the greene wax ſent out that year, which Nihills be iſſues, that the Sheriff that is appoſed doth ſay be nothing worth, and illeviable for the inſufficiencie of the parties that ſhould pay them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Clerk of the Nihills doth write them out in a roll of parchment, and ſetteth them in the Court where they lie and under the titles of thoſe Streats from whence they come, and where they are marked as afore in <hi>Rottulo,</hi> which Roll he delivereth into the Treaſurors Remembrancers office, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:125850:56"/>
upon the ſame there be ſo many <hi>Fieri fac:</hi> inrolled againſt ſuch Sheriffs as have their iſſues marked in <hi>Rottulo,</hi> and Nihills which they returned, to know why they ſhould not Anſwer the kings Majeſties the ſame Nihills which they did returne for good iſſues, and leviable upon the parties on whoſe head they were ſet, which Sheriffs ſo ſummoned, muſt either come in and juſtifie them leviable, and prove them, and then he that Nihill'd them, or elſe the Sheriff that cannot ſo juſtifie them, muſt pay the ſame himſelfe, whereby it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the Court and lawe provideth, that the Kings Majeſtie ſhall looſe nothing that he hath right to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Seale of the Court</head>
               <p>IS the Officer that keepeth the Seale of the Court all terme time under every Chanceller, and is bound to Attend and ſeale all proceſſe, Commiſſions, Injunctions, Exemplifications, and writts whatſoever,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:125850:56"/>
that be brought to him in Court, 'or out of Court, from any of the Officers that have Authoritie to make the ſame (except he have contrary Commandement, or his maſters, or ſome of the cheife Officers of the Court do make ſtay ſometimes of ſome of them for ſome ſpeciall matter thought meete and expedient) who in many caſes hath Fees for ſundrie of them whem they be ſealed for the partie, and not for the King, but upon allowance at the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cheife Uſher</head>
               <p>IS he that by inheritance hath the keeping of the Court, the Exchequer Chamber, and the howſe with all the Appertenance where the Court dines, when they ſit about the Kings buſineſſe, who maketh proviſion for all the neceſſaries both of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer and of the receit, and hath allowance at every liberate thereof againe, and ſeeth to all places of the Court, that all doores, cheſts, Records, and things be in ſafty from fire, water, or ſpoile, and giveth knowledge
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:125850:57"/>
of them accordingly, and as it needs, and hath the overſight of the reſidue of the Uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the ſix ordinary Meſſengers of the Court, that they deliver truly from time to time to the Sheriffs and all others the Kings proceſſe; and bring the Sheriffs Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ls ſubſcribed from time to time for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of the ſame, which he doth exammine by his Book that he keepeth of the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of all the Kings proceſſe every terme, wherein is ſet and totalled up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of writts and proceſſe that goeth out every terme, and to what Sheriff they be ſent, and out of what Office in the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Marſhall of the Court</head>
               <p>IS an Officer to whome the Court Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſometime the Cuſtodie of ſuch a one as they will not for the time ſend to the Fleete and yet is thought meete in that wiſe for ſome Cauſe to be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
               <p>He aſſigneth in open Court, all Sheriffs, Eſcheators, Cuſtomers, Collectors of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:125850:57"/>
and Fifteens, and ſuch like Accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants when they have taken their oath to the Auditor, before whom every of them ſhall account, whereof he keepeth an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary book, and deviſeth ſo by the Court that the Accountants ſhould never chooſe his own Auditor, to practiſe or help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by it.</p>
               <p>He receiveth all Offices that Eſcheators do find <hi>(Virtute Officij)</hi> and delivereth them in Court whereof he ſhould keep a Book, and ſo deliver the Originall into the Treaſurers Remembrancers Office to be delivered by the Roll of Streats, there to the parcell makers to charge the ſame in ſuch Eſcheators parcells when he cometh in to account.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Foure Ordinary Uſhers</head>
               <p>BE ſuch as with their ſtick, attend upon the cheif Officers and Barons of the Court, at their coming to, or their going from <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and call all Juries, and all perſons appointed them in open Court, and fetch them; they are appointed out of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:125850:58"/>
Court, and uſe to make in open Court, all noiſes, ſilence, and proclamations, calling of witneſſes, returns, and of all cacountants, both at and after their dayes of prefixion, and times appointed them by Law, and the courſe of the Court, and to do all other things that are commanded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Prayſors of the Court</head>
               <p>BE cercain Officers of late made firſt by Sir <hi>John Bacon,</hi> when he was Under-Treaſurer, without ſee of the Prince, and they praiſe all Wares and Merchandize, that information is put againſt in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, as ſeiled here in the Port of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> or in any other Ports of the Realme, as Cuſtome and Subſidie thereof not payd, which Praiſors of old time were choſen here of Merchants of the City, as it fel out, and as they were taken up by the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff to prize the ſaid Wares, whereof they had skill, and now by the uſe of time, the ſayd ſtanding Prayſors, that are appointed by the Vice Treaſurer to be certain, have a certain ſmall fee a peice, of and upon every appraiſement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:125850:58"/>
               <head>The four Tellers of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt</head>
               <p>ARe Officers of the Receit, that receive to the Kings Majeſties uſe, all monyes payd in there, and do make new dated parchment bills, under their hands with ſuch Counties names, letters, words, and ſumm in the ſame Bills, as ſerves briefly to make it to appear for what cauſe, and by whom, every ſuch ſum of mony to them is payd, and many yeares ſince they were in the Receit, <hi>Ponderatores,</hi> and <hi>Fuſores,</hi> at which time it ſeemeth the mony was ſo wel kept, that the tale fell out even with the waights, and <hi>Fuſores</hi> were then melters of the mony, to make aſſay of it into the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, that it might be weighed.</p>
               <p>Theſe now deliver their parchment Bills to the party that payeth the mony, but caſt the ſame down out of the Office by a hole made for that purpoſe, upon the Boord of the Receipt, whither the party repaireth, and prayeth a Tally to be ſtricken for him
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:125850:59"/>
according to his Bill caſt down, which Bills heretofore were oftentimes carried away by the parties that thought the ſame only a ſufficient diſcharge for their mony, and were yet afterwards much vexed for the ſame with proceſs.</p>
               <p>They may receive all mens mony that are to pay any into the Receit, ſave the generall Receivers, and the Biſhops Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors mony, who are aſſigned to each of them ſpecially by name, that their pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and arrerages may even appear at the eye, becauſe they uſe much to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind hand, and are for the Non-payments to be charged by the Statute. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not now pay any mony for fees, or upon any privy ſeal or Warrant, without a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benter firſt ſent from the Auditor of the Receipt, whereby is known ſtill moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly what mony is payd, and what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in every of their hands from time to time.</p>
               <p>They keep every of them a rough booke of every days receipts, as they fall out in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very kind of payment made unto them, and they title their ſayd bookes into half years receits, as thus, <hi>Michaelmas</hi> receit to <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:125850:59"/>
and <hi>Paſch.</hi> Receipt, for all monies Payd from <hi>Eaſter</hi> to <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> and their weekly Certificates by the ſame to the Lord Treaſurer and others, as they are commanded, what every of them hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p>They make every half year out of this their rough book, a fair paper book of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their ſaid halfe years receits, and from their rough books they do ſort out in the ſame, all Receits of Revenues together, which be of payments only of ancient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of the Exchequer, and of the late Augmentation Court, and not of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny granted the Crown by Parliament.</p>
               <p>Then next to the Revenue, they ſort in the ſame fair book all Receits of mony granted to the Crown by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or of Subſides of the late Subſidies of the Clergy, the fifteens, the yearly Tenths of the Clergy <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and title every of them after their Nature, and as they fall out by the firſt and ſecond payment, and in this fair book, every of them doth ſum up very perfectly all the ſaid ſeverall kinds of Receits, and doth totall up thereupon their whole years receit with the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:125850:60"/>
in their hands of their laſt halfe years accounts before.</p>
               <p>By which fair book every of them do make their count books, they deliver half yearly to the Auditor of the receit to take their accounts which Counter books be of whole skins of parchment written on both ſides, and on the top of the firſt skin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is ſet as it were <hi>Comp. A. B. Term. Michaelis octave Regis Jacobi finium ad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num incipiente tempore C. Domini Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri Angliae.</hi> Then is there a great down right line, and drawn in the midſt of every the ſayd skins on the left hand of every ſuch line, which receits and payments be never totalled up by the Tellers, but are left to their auditors to do, who caſteth up the totall of their Receits, with their ſayd laſt half years Remainder, ſo maketh their full charge, and then doth he totall up their payments in the other ſide, and in the end doth make clear remain of that half years accounts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:125850:60"/>
               <head>The Clerk of the Pelle.</head>
               <p>IS called by the ancient Records (as I learn) <hi>Clericus Dm. Theſauri,</hi> who keepeth the Pell in parchment called <hi>Pellis Recepti,</hi> wherein he entreth every Tellers ſaid parchment Bill with his name on it, and writeth under every ſuch parchment Bill that is entred <hi>Recordatur,</hi> which firſt Entry (as I learn) now is made in a paper book, and hath been begun but of late days to keep the Pelle fair, and from ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing as they ſay, when men are forced a little to mend the Letter of their Tallyes, but even before the firſt Entry of every Tellers Bill was made in the Pell it ſelf in Parchment, and done in open Court, and ſo it is now afterwards ingroſſed up by the ſayd book at leiſure.</p>
               <p>He alſo in old time kept the parcell of iſſues in parchment, which were called, <hi>Pellis Exitus,</hi> wherein was entred every dayes iſſuing of any of the ſayd monyes, and by whom, what Warrant, Privy ſeal, or Bill it was payed, which of late was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:125850:61"/>
to be kept by him in the old Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers time, and thought then very neecſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but now ſince (as I learn) it is layd down again, as thought not ſo neceſſary, the Receipt being ordered as it is at this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Cutter of the Tallyes.</head>
               <p>IS the Officer that provideth a ſeaſoned and proportionable haſell for the Tallies, and cutteth the ſame to fit length for the purpoſe, and doth ſomewhat thwite every ſtick thereof into four ſquare ſides, that they may be better cloven and written up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and he caſteth them into the Court from time to time, when any of them be called for, and receiveth his fee of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that ſueth it out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Comptrollers of the Pell</head>
               <p>BE the two Chamberlains Clarks that ſhould either of them keep a Control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Pell, and make forth in onp
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:125850:61"/>
Court, like entries of every Tellers bill into like Pells of Parchment, as the Clark of the Pell doth, and that <hi>Verbatim,</hi> which now here be ſometimes kept, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not, the ſees thereof are ſo ſmall, and the Pell by proceſſe of time is grown ſo great, that no man would willingly Write the Controllment for the ſee.</p>
               <p>They were wont alſo in ancient time, either of them to keep a like controllment of the ſayd Pell of Iſſues, and to make both theirs <hi>Verbatim,</hi> agreeing with the Pell of iſſues as afore, kept by the Clark of the Pell, which theſe many years was not kept by them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Auditor of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt.</head>
               <p>IS the Officer that taketh up ſtraight eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tellers Bill after it is marked <hi>Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur,</hi> by the Clark of the Pell, and entred by the controllers of the Pell likewiſe, and ſyleth it ſtraight upon a fyle, then h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Clark called <hi>Scriptor Talliar. &amp; contratal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaram,</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:125850:62"/>
for whom his Maſter hath a ſee, writeth double upon every Tally the whole Letter of the Tellers, that where it is clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, both the Tally and the ſtock thereof may have like Letter upon it, being dry, doth deliver the ſame ſecond to the under Chamberlaines to cleave.</p>
               <p>He the ſaid Auditor doth enter all the ſaid parchment bills again in a fair book that is to him as <hi>Pellis Recepti,</hi> and by thoſe ſame he doth ſee what monyes every Teller receiveth weekly, and of whom, and what every half year in his <hi>Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Receipt and his <hi>Paſch.</hi> Receipt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he certifieth weekly to the Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and others as he is commanded, how all the mony of the Receipt particularly is payd, and received. By which certificate it is ſeen and examined, whether every of the Tellers Certificates weekly be true and juſtifiable.</p>
               <p>He maketh now to every of the Tellers a Debentur, before any of them can pay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mony out of the receit, be it upon Fines, Privy Seal, or Warrants that they pay, which is to be made, and is very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly done, that upon any reſtraint of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:125850:62"/>
payment given by the Lord Treaſure or his order, his Lordſhip may be ſure to have his Majeſties mony kept ſtill undefrayed, while the ſame be ſet again a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Liberty.</p>
               <p>He receiveth every of the Tellers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter books in parchment, every half year, and taketh every of their accounts by the ſame, and cauſeth the Tellers to reform his Titles, and diviſions in them if they be not orderly and plain enough for their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and then doth he caſt up every of their ſaid parchment bills of the half year, their Counter book before, and ſeeth the total of them; after, he caſteth up the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of every of their Counter books to ſee if the totall of every of them doth agree with the total of their parchment bills, and ſo doth make up fair the totall ſumm of every of their Counter books, that be agreeable with their bills, and they that have any er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror be rejected, and examined while the ſame may be ſound and made to agree with their half years Bills, and thereupon are totalled up as the reſt. To which total, he caſeth every Tellers half years remain, and maketh his whole charge, and ſo allowing every of them their payments and deduc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:125850:63"/>
ons, he maketh every of their cleere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines upon their Counter bookes for that halfe year alſo, as he had done before, and ſo declareth all the ſaid Counter bookes halfe yearly before my Lord Treaſuror, when it is his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>He keepeth the black book of the Receit, and the Lord Treaſurors key of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury both where the ancient leagues of the Realme, and all the Perambulations of the Forreſts, and the Records of Juſtice Itinerant, and divers other Records do lie, Both in the old Court of wards, and in the old Parliament houſe in the Cloiſter at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter,</hi> where no ſearch can be made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that key come, with both the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines keyes thereof.</p>
               <p>He doth (now of late) ſe every Tellers money locked, and ſealed up in the new Treaſurie, made for that purpoſe, when it is my Lord Treaſurers pleaſure, or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo to have it to be; and keepeth or delivereth the key as he Commandeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:125850:63"/>
               <head>The two under Chamberlains</head>
               <p>BE both the Chamberlaines deputies for the Receit, and when the Tallies are written upon as before is declared unto them, one of them doth Cleeve the ſame even in the middeſt between the double let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Tallie mentioned before, and then the Cleever taking the ſtick, and the other foile, and the Clerk of the Pell and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troller the Book where the ſaid Tellers bills were recorded, the Cleever ſaith <hi>Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> and readeth the ſtock aloud, and ſo his fellow The Clerk of the Pell and his two Comptrollers ſeeing the ſtock to agree with them all, the ſame is by and by deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the partie, and the foyle ſtraight caſt into the Chamberlaines Cheſt, where they keep all their foiles, together with their knives, and the Book of Doomeſday, while the Joyners fetch them away from time to time as they be occupied.</p>
               <p>In which Cheſt alſo, be kept the keyes of the Treaſurie under three locks, whereof
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:125850:64"/>
the auditor of the Receit hath one key, and the two Chamberlaines another key, and the Uſher of the Receit that is in the Kings guift another key, who doth now attend by his deputie, and is to do all things there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, that other Uſhers uſe to do, and keepeth the Receit as the Uſher by Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance doth the Exchequer.</p>
               <p>They make all ſearches in the Treaſurie for any Record at the ſuite of the parties, and Exemplifications of the ſame, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Fees are divided betweene them, and the keeper of my Lord Treaſurors key as of long time hath beene accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Fower ordinary Meſsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the Receit</head>
               <p>BE the Purſevants only Attendant upon my Lord Treaſuror to carry his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips letters and percepts to all the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Controllers, and Searchers through <hi>England,</hi> and to ride and goe where it is his Lordſhips pleaſure to Command.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:125850:64"/>
            <head>The Articles of the late Court of Augmentations and Revenues of the Crowne annexed to the Court of Exchequer at <hi>Westminſter</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Lord Treaſuror.</head>
               <p n="1">1 FIrſt all Honers, lands, tenements, poſſeſſions, amd all other heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments which are within the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey, rule, and order of the Augmentations of the Crowne, and the Arrerage, of the ſame, ſhall be received, leavied, and gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed form hence forth by the Sheriffs of every Shire and Countie within the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> where the ſaid Honers, Caſtles, Mannors, lands, Tenements &amp; other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizaments do lye, or by any other perſon or perſons that ſhall be appointed by the Lord Treaſurer and the Court thereafter, which
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:125850:65"/>
Receit the ſaid Sheriff of every countie, or other accountant ſo appointed, ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and pay the Revenue thereof at the Receit of the Exchequer in manner and forme as hereafter ſhall be declared.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> the Revenues in wales, ſhall be yearly received by the Chamberlaine there, or by any other perſon or perſons that ſhall be appointed by the ſaid Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and the Court as is aforeſaid, the ſame to pay at the receit aforeſaid, and to be bound by Recognizances for the payments thereof according to the direction of the Court.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Sheriffs or other accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptants to have a tallie of reward yearly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of their ſeverall charges if it ſhal be thought fit by the Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, Chancellor, Chamberlaines, and Barons or by three of them whereof the Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuror to be one.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Item,</hi> that every Sheriff of <hi>England,</hi> or other accomptant ſhall be charged with the Revenues aforeſaid in his account from <hi>Michalmas,</hi> to <hi>Michelmas,</hi> according to the Ancient lawes and Cuſtomes of the ſaid Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:125850:65"/>
5 <hi>Item,</hi> all ſuch ſummes of money as ſhalbe due at the Feaſts of the birth of our Lord, The annunciation of our Lady, or at the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> for the ſaid Revenues, with the Arrearage depending upon all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer accounts, ſhall be charged in to the ſaid Sheriff, or other Accomptants in their views, and ſhall make the ſaid view before the Feaſt of the Aſcention of our Lord year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to pay all ſuch ſummes of money as ſhalbe found due upon the ſame before the Feaſt of Penticoſt then next enſueing, and where they be payable at <hi>Penticoſt,</hi> thoſe rents to be payed before the <hi>Nativitie</hi> of Saint John the Baptiſt then next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Item,</hi> if any former accomptant or debtor hath paid any ſummes of money at the receit aforeſaid, before the making of the view aforeſaid, that then the ſaid Sheriff or other accomptant ſhall be diſcharged by the payment thereof being of Record with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further ſuite or Charge in the ſaid view of account.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Item,</hi> that all ſuch ſummes as ſhalbe due for the ſaid Revenue at the Feaſt of <hi>Michaelmas</hi> and <hi>Saint Martin,</hi> with the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:125850:66"/>
Arrerages due upon all former accounts, ſhalbe paid at the receit of the Exchequer by the Sheriffs or other receivers, or accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptants (that is to ſay) as much as ſhalbe due at <hi>Michaelnsas,</hi> before the Feaſt of the Nativitie of our Lord God, And aſmuch as ſhalbe due at <hi>Saint Martin,</hi> to be paid into the receit before the twentieth day of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> then next inſueing, or otherwiſe make declaration unto the ſaid Court of Exchequer of the payment thereof by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of ſufficient Warrant.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Item,</hi> that every Sheriff, and other Accomptant ſhall appeare to his account in his owne proper perſon, or by his ſufficient Deputie Authoriſed in writing under his hand and ſeale in Hillary Terme, and there to take an Oath according to an Ancient uſage of the ſaid Exchequer, and the ſame Warrant in writing to be delivered into the Treaſurors Remembrancers office and there ſhall be filed, and entred of record, without taking any Fee, or reward for the ſame.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Sheriff or other accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, or Accomptants, or his, or their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Deputie or Attorney after his or their
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:125850:66"/>
Appearances, to make their accounts for the ſaid Revenues before the twentie fourth of <hi>February</hi> then next after, and the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor taking the ſaid accounts ſhall deliver the ſame accounts ingroſſed in parchment Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed and allowed by the hands ſubſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of the Lord Treaſuror, Chancellor, Vice-treaſuror, and Barons of the ſaid Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, or by three of them at the leaſt, whereof the Lord Treaſuror or Vice-trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuror to be one, And with the hand of the ſaid Auditor likewiſe ſubſcribed into the office of the Pipe within the ſaid Court of Exchequer before the twentieth day of <hi>March,</hi> then next following, as further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe thereupon may be made if cauſe ſhall ſo require.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Item,</hi> that the Lord Treaſuror, Chancellor, Chamberlaines, Under-treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and Barons, or three of them whereof the Lord Treaſuror to be one, and in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the Under treaſuror ſhall have full power and Authoritie by their diſcretions from time to time, to give Allowances aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the Farmors and Accomptant for the yearly reparations and other Allowan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as alſo to every perſon and perſons
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:125850:67"/>
that ſhalbe hereafter appointed by them or by the more part of them, for the doeing and executing of any proceſſe or other thing concerning the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Item,</hi> all Records of the ſaid Court of the Augmentations that doth concerne exemtion of any proceſſe for Indentures, Recognizances, obligations, and all records of Books of orders and decrees concerning the premiſſes. ſhall remaine in the Charge of the Kings Remembrancer of the ſaid Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer in ſuch place or places, as by the Lord Treaſuror and the Court ſhalbe from time to time appointed</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Item,</hi> that all Commiſſions for woodſales, and Commiſſions for ſurvey of any part or parcell of the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſhall be made hereafter by the Treaſurors Remembrancer of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Item,</hi> all records and Books of the ſaid Court of the Augmentations of the Inrollment of Leaſes, and the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paines of the ſaid Leaſes and Warrants for making of the ſame, and all accompts that ſhall remaine in the ſaid Court concerning
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:125850:67"/>
anie thing or matter within their old order and ſurvey of the ſame ſhall be and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the Charge of the Clerke of the Pipe of the ſaid Exchequer in ſuch place as the ſaid Lord Treaſuror and Court ſhall a ward, ſo that proceſſe may be made upon them <hi>Unde ſuperius,</hi> as long as the caſe ſhal require.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Item,</hi> that all ſealed Evidences, Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, Court rolls, and other writings, and miniments whatſoever, touching the ſaid Revenues, be placed in the Treaſurie howſe that ſhalbe appointed for that purpoſe by the Lord Treaſurer and others the head Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of that Court.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Item,</hi> Accounts to be taken every yeare and the Ingroſſments in forme as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid to remaine in the Charge of the Clerk of the Pipe in ſuch place as ſhall be appointed by the Lord Treaſuror and other the head Officers of that Court amongſt the Evidences and the records of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue of the land, ſevered from the Ancient records of the Exchequer.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Item,</hi> that all Stewards of Leets and Courts, ſhall yearly double their Court Rolls in parchment, and certifie one part
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:125850:68"/>
thereof ſubſcribed with the hand of the Receivors before the Audit into the Court of Exchequer wherein ſhould be contained the Fines made among the Cuſtomary Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, the Heriotts, the Amerciaments, the woodſales, and other Caſualties with a declaration of needfull reparations preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Homage making thereof a Streat to the Sheriffs of the Shire, or to ſuch other Accomptant, as ſhalbe appointed to the receit thereof as he may thereupon make his receit and payment upon the end of his account, and that noe reparations be made at any time but by Warrant from the Court under three of the Officers hands, whereof the Lord Treaſuror or Under-treaſuror to be one, And the other part of the double of the ſaid Court Rolls to remain in the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, where the ſaid Courts be kept.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Item,</hi> no woodſales ſhall be made without a Commiſſion from my Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuror, and two ſuch others of the Court as he ſhall call to have at that time and in his abſence the Under treaſuror calling to him two of the ſaid Court.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Item,</hi> that noe Steward, Bayliff, or Woodward be admitted, but onely by the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:125850:68"/>
Lord Treaſuror, Chancellor, and Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, Vice-treaſuror, and Barons of the ſaid Exchequer, or three of them at the leaſt, whereof the Lord Treaſuror or Under-treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to be one of the ſame Officers to paſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Seale of the Exchequer by the Lord Treaſurors Aſſignement under his hand, and the ſame Bill or Bills to be made in the Office of the Pipe there to be entred of Record, filed, and kept, for the yearly Allowance of the Fees, wages; and rewards of any perſon or perſons, as hereafter ſhall be appointed to any of the ſaid Offices.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>Item,</hi> the Accounts of Hamper, the Butierage, the Staple of Callis, and the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the Courts there, the Priſes, the Mints, the great Guardrobe, the Cuſtomes of the Ports of <hi>Cheſter, Barwick,</hi> and <hi>Callice,</hi> to be yearly taken and ingroſſed by the Audi, tors of the ſaid Exchequer according to the Ancient lawes of the ſaid Court, and as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore they have beene accuſtomed before the Erection of the Court of ſurvey and Augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Revenue.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Item,</hi> where in times paſt there hath beene continually 6. Auditors ſerving in the ſaid Court of Exchequer, whereof at this day and of long time hath beene remaineing but 5
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:125850:69"/>
having ten pounds for every year for his fee, it is now ordered, that there ſhall be ſeven to have yearly twenty pounds for his and their fees, and that every of the ſaid Auditors be perſonally reſident upon his Office.</p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Item,</hi> That every Teller of the Receit be likewiſe attendant upon his Office, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame in his own perſon, and not by Deputy upon the loſſe of his Office, and fee.</p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>Item,</hi> For that the order, eſtabliſhment and uniting of this Court be perfectly eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with exerciſe, proof, and experience of the ſame, the Kings Highneſs is pleaſed, that the Lord Treaſurer, and the ſaid Court of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, ſhould have full power and authority from time to time to amend, reform, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, any clauſe or Article aforeſaid, and to add to, or diminiſh any thing that ſhall be found neceſſary for the amendment of the ſame, and to make ſuch further orders from time to time, as to the Court ſhalbe thought expedient.</p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>Item,</hi> That all Rents and ſervices reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved be anſwered in the ſaid Court of Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equer, and paid in the ſaid Receipt, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all debts, arrerages of accounts, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dutyes and ſumms of mony which have been anſwered in the ſaid Exchequer, be payd in the ſayd receipt.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:125850:69"/>
24. <hi>Item;</hi> To call into the Court of Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, all perſons accountable in ſuch manner and form, as they ought to have been called in the ſaid Court of augmentation.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>Item,</hi> That all Records of late being in the ſayd Court diſſolved, and belonging to the ſame Court ſhall be recorded of the ſame court of Exchequer, and of the ſame force and ſtrength, as they were in the ſaid late Court diſſolved.</p>
               <p n="26">26. <hi>Item,</hi> A Leagure to be made of all ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialties brought into the ſaid Court.</p>
               <p n="27">27. <hi>Item,</hi> That all Letters Patents, Grants, Leafes, and other Aſſurances, made by the ſayd late Courts diſſolved, ſhalbe of the ſame force and ſtrength, as they were in the ſayd late Courts diſſolved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Articles of the uniting of the late Court of uniting of firſt Fruits and Tenths, to the Court of Exchequer at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1 FIrſt, Her Highneſs doth ordain, that all the Records of the ſaid Court, of the firſt Fruits and Tenths, ſhall be hereafter pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:125850:70"/>
in the ſaid Exchequer, and ſhall be of the ſame force and ſtrength, as they were in the ſaid Courts of the ſaid firſt fruits and Tenths.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> her highneſs is pleaſed and ordaineth that there ſhall be in the ſaid Exchequer, a certain Office, called the Office of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer of the firſt Fruits and Tenths which Office, for divers and ſundry great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations for and at the firſt erection only, ſhalbe exerciſed by two perſons by her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be nominated, which ſhall joyntly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the ſame office during their lives, and after the death of the Survivor of them, the ſaid office to be exerciſed by one of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> That all Records belonging to the ſame court of the firſt Fruits and Tenths, ſhall be in the charge and keeping of the ſaid Officer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> That the ſaid Officer ſhall make and deliver the true values of all ſpirituall promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, dignities, and benefits within the Realm of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and other the Queens Dominions to ſuch perſons as ſhall ſue for them, taking for the ſame like fees as were wont to be paid before the diſſolution of the firſt fruits and Tenths.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> The ſame Officer ſhall take compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions of the firſt Fruits of every Arch Biſhop
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:125850:70"/>
prick, Arch-Desconry, Deanry, Prebendary, Parſonage, Vicaridge, and of every other dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, office, benefice, promotion ſpirituall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Item,</hi> The ſame officer to make all wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings obligatory, Indentures, and all other writings concerning the ſame firſt fruits and tenths, and ſhall ſee the ſame ſealed and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, by the parties to the Queens highneſs uſe, and alſo ſhall make Acquittances and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcharges to ſuch as ſhal pay their mony in hand without making bonds for the ſame, taking fees accuſtomed of the parties for the ſame.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Lord Treaſurer.</head>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Lord Treaſuror to call ſuch perſons as ſhall pleaſe him to his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance at the declaration of the foreſaid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, or any officer or auditor of the ſame Court, that to them ſhal be thought meet for the paſſing of the ſame accounts.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Item,</hi> The accountant or accountants that ſhall not come to determin his or their accounts in form aforeſaid, his or their goods and lands ſhall be ſeiſed to the Queens uſe, <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine diſtrictionis,</hi> and ſhall looſe the benefit thereof, and that ſhall have the allowance of the ſame in diſcharge of his debt according to the ancient cuſtom of the Exchequer.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:125850:71"/>
9. <hi>Item,</hi> all <hi>Sci. fac.</hi> attachments, and writs of diſtreſſes for debts, or accounts concerning the premiſſes, ſhalbe made by the Treaſurers Remembrancer from time to time, as to the diſcretion of the Court in that be half ſhall be thought meet and convenient, according to the ancient cuſtom and courſe of the Court.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Item,</hi> All Letters Patents of any Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, land, tenements, or other hereditaments or concerning any annuities, pardons, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like, ſhalbe inrolled in ſuch office of the ſaid Exchequer, as by the diſcretion of the Lord Treaſurer and the ſaid Court ſhalbe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, the parties to pay fines according to the ordinance and ſtatute in that behalf pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Item,</hi> All recognizances of payments of any farm, or any debt, of or for any part of the premiſſes, to be inrolled in the Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers office, and to be taken in the open Court, when the Term is open, &amp; if the Term be not open, then by the chief Baron, and in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, by any of the Barons, and by force of a <hi>Dedim. Poteſtat.</hi> if neceſſity ſhall require, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for every ſuch recognizince, taken out of the court, 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> only whatſoever number of perſons be bound in the ſame, and for the entry of the ſame recognizance, the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:125850:71"/>
ſhall have, and take for his fee of and for every Recognizance of 41. and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, 3 s. 4 d and no other or more Fees to be taken for a Recognizance, whatſoever number of perſons be bound in the ſame.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>Item,</hi> that the ſaid Sheriffs or other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptants ſhall yearly pay all ſuch ſummes of money, as ſhal be due to anie perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for any Annuities, Fees, penſions iſſueing or going out of any of the premiſſes according to their grants allowed and inrolled, unleſſe they ſhall have ſpeciall Commandement by the Court to the contrarie.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Item,</hi> that the Farmors, and Leſſes ſhall be bound to the Queen, and by Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance to performe their Covenants in their Leaſes in ſuch forme, as by the Court ſhall be ordered.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Item,</hi> all Warrants for leaſes to paſſe by the Lord Treaſuror, and if the yearly rent of the land to be letten, ſhall be above the ſumme of forty ſhillings by the yeare, then the ſame leaſe to paſſe under the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and if the rent be above the value of 71. 13 ſ. 4 d. then every ſuch leſſee to pay the Fees of the Signet and privy Seale, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fore in like Caſes hath beene accuſtomed; And if the land to be letten, doe paſſe not the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:125850:72"/>
yearly rent of 40 s. then the Leaſe to paſſe the ſeale of the ſame Court of Exchequer paying 6 s. 8 d. to the Queens uſe, 3 s. 4 d. to the Chancellor of the ſaid Court, and 4 d. to one appointed to Attend the ſeale for his Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and wax. And the ſaid Leaſes under the value of 40 s. to be alwayes made by the Clark of the Pipe, and filed together for every yeare by themſelves, and there to be inrolled within the ſaid Office, as the ſaid Clark of the Pipe may report the Indentures for the more ſurety of the parties, taking for the inroll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſhall be ordered by the Court.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Lord Treaſuror ſhall not have any Authoritie to make any leaſe in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of any part or parcell of the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or of any woods, or anie Mannors in groſſe for the terme of certaine yeares without the Queens highneſſe ſpeciall Warrant to him to be directed in that behalfe, and then Warrant to be made by the Lord Treaſuror of <hi>England</hi> in forme aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Item,</hi> the Lord Treaſuror taking to him the Advice of the Chancellor, under-treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and cheife Baron or two of them, ſhall have Authoritie to aſſeſſe Fines for any Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of any part or parcell of the premiſſes to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:125850:72"/>
be made by the ſaid Lord Treaſuror in forme aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Item,</hi> the ſame Officer to write, and make all manner of proceſſe, Commiſſions, Entries, Books, Judgments, and decrees of the Court, with all other writings and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoever, aſwell for the arrerages of ſuch firſt fruits as for all Tenths, and Subſidies of the Clergie due to her highneſſe heires, and Succeſſors by ſuch ſpeciall perſons their Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Farmers, and occupiers, taking therefore ſuch Fees of the parties, as were uſed before the diſſolution of the ſame Court of firſt fruits and Tenthes.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Item,</hi> all Certificats returned upon any Commiſſion iſſueing out of the ſaid Court of Exchequer concerning anie firſt fruits, Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ths, or Subſidies aforeſaid the valuation of any Ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fice, or promotion ſpirituall omitted in the firſt Taxation or otherwiſe, for any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accuſtomed to be determined in the ſaid Court of the Exchequer in the charge of the ſaid Office, and there to be ordered.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>Item,</hi> all ſuch Certificats as the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops and other Collectors of the Tenths, and Subſides of the Clergie, made againſt the Incumbents reſuſing to pay their Tenths and Subſides being exhibited before the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:125850:73"/>
Court of Exchequer, and by them allowed, ſhall remaine in the Charge of the ſaid office of the Remembrancer of the firſt fruits, and Tenths, in the place to be appointed for the ſame, to the end that proceſſe may be made againſt ſuch Incumbents as be in them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Item,</hi> that the ſame Officer ſhall year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make a Leger of all Compoſitions of firſt fruits taken, and to be taken, wherein ſhall be contained the name and ſhire of the Benefice ſo compounded for, the ſamm, and name of the Incumbent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Engliſh Bills and the proceedinges there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon in the Exchequer.</head>
               <p>AN Engliſh bil is a petition in Engliſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by the plaintiff to the Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer Chanceller and Barons of the exchequer in caſe where the plaintiff ſuppoſeth he hath right to recover the poſſeſſion of lands or goods deteined from him or debts due to him or to have remedy for ſome other wrong done to him by the defendant that he hath noe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence nor ſpecialty to ſhew forth nor can make any ſuch proofe as is required by the ſtrict courſe of the Common Law to recover
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:125850:73"/>
or have remedy for the ſame, but ſuppoſeth that it lyeth in the defendants owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and that he will confeſſe the ſame in his anſwere. And in caſe where the plaintiffs ſued at Common Law for the poſſeſſion of any lands or for any goods, chattells, Debts or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things againſt which he can make noe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient defence by ſtrict courſe of the Common Law but in equity and good conſcience ought to be releived and get either wholly diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or the extremity mitigated and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſuppoſeth that the defendant will confeſſe in his anſwere the truth of the matter by him alledged.</p>
               <p>Every plaintiff that ſhall exhibite any ſuch bill ought to be priviledged either in perſon as an Officer or Clerk of the Court or ſervant to ſome of them or an accomptant or Debtor to the king or otherwiſe or elſe in the cauſe as if that concerne the king in the inheritance, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion or intreſt of any lands, tithes, offices, goods, chattels or Debts wherein the plaintiff likewiſe pretendeth to have Intereſt in right of the King. or if the plaintiff beſued by Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh bill or action or extent or other proces in the ſame Court for the ſame matter.</p>
               <p>The Kings Attorney alſo may exhibite En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Bills in the Exchequer for any matter
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:125850:74"/>
concerning the King in inheritance or profits and in like manner any perſon that findeth himſelfe greived in any cauſe proſecuted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him for and on the behalfe of the King or any patent by grant of the King may exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite his Engliſh bill againſt the Kings Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and ſuch others as are intereſted in the cauſe to be releived in equity. In which caſe the plaintiff muſt Attend the Kings Attorney with a Coppy of his bill and procureth him to anſwere the ſame and the Kings Attorney may call any that are intereſted in the Cauſe or any officer or others to inſtruct him herein touching the makeing his anſwer ſo as the King be not prejudiced thereby and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is to be put in without oath.</p>
               <p>The parties in every ſuch bill between party and party muſt ſerve the defendant with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Snbpena</hi> or if the defendant be a Baron of Parliament ſpirituall or Temporall with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letter under the hands of the Lord Treaſurer Chancellor Barons or ſome of them whereby he muſt berequired to appeare at a day certain contained in the writ or letter proces of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pena</hi> may be ſued forth either before or after the Bill exhibited And if the Defendant do not appere at the day of returne of the writ then upon <hi>Affidav.</hi> made of the ſervinge thereof an
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:125850:74"/>
Atachment is made of courſe againſt him for his contempts and after an <hi>al. pl.</hi> atachment an attachment with exclamation and after that either a writ of attachment of rebellion directed to the ſheriff or a Commiſſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion directed to ſuch Commiſſioners as the plaintiff wil name for which Commiſſion there muſt be warrant of the court but when aletter is made to be ſent to any Baron or Biſhopps for apparance before the Bill be in and if he will not appear upon that then proces of <hi>Sub-pena</hi> muſt be ſerved and upon default then proces of Contempt as aforeſaid And the like courſe of proces is to be perſued againſt the defendant at the ſuite of the Kings Attorney.</p>
               <p>When the defendant doth appear if the Bill be not put in he may move to be diſmiſſed with coſts, whereupon the Court doth uſually give three or four dayes to the plaintiff to put in his Engliſh bill or the Defendant to be diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with coſts upon a bill of coſts to be Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by him to one of the Barons to be taxed.</p>
               <p>And if the defendant do appear upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of contempt he muſt pay coſts ſuch as the Court ſhall think fit according to the number of the proces that hath been proſecuted againſt him but the ordinary Coſts in ten ſhillings upon each Attachment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:125850:75"/>
After the defendant hath appeared he hath eight dayes of courſe to make his anſwer to the bill and if he do that not with in that time a Rule is given of courſe in the Book of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance for an Attachment within fower dayes, the defendants Attorney being called thereunto.</p>
               <p>If the defendant do Demur upon the Bill for that neither the plaintiff nor the cauſe is privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for want of ſufficient matter of the bill or put in a plea in Bar of the proceeding upon the Bill, The plaintiff if he will maintaine his Bil muſt move the Court for a day to heare the Counſell of both ſides and the Bill and Demurrer (if need be) if the Counſell do not agree in opening the matter.</p>
               <p>If the defendant do plead any matter to bar the proceedings upon the bill (other Then matter of Record of the ſame Court) he muſt be ſworne to his plea as he likewiſe muſt be ſworne to his anſwere if he anſwere in the cheif of what quality ſoever the defendant be Except it be the Kings Attorney who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth a bill againſt the King or a Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion who are ſued by the name of theire Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration.</p>
               <p>Alſo if the defendant doe make an inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient anſwere the plaintiff muſt put in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:125850:75"/>
in writing and move the Court to give the defendant a day to amend or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his anſwere in which caſe if the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant be in Towne he is to take notice by the Order and to perform the ſame. But if he be gone before he is to be ſerved with a <hi>Subpoena ad faciendum meliorem reſponſionem</hi> if his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere be over ruled upon heareing or an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment made againſt him or an inſufficient anſwere is to anſwere.</p>
               <p>The defendant that hath dayes aforeſaid either upon demurer, plea, or inſufficient an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere if he cannot maintaine the ſame but that the Court doth order him to make a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anſwere, he muſt pay ſuch coſts to the plaintiff as the Court ſhall think fit, if he do maintaine his demurer he is to be diſmiſſed with coſts.</p>
               <p>If the defendant put in plea where in he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth matter of record to diſable the perſon of the plaintiff as outlawry or the like which is no bar to the matter but a delay of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing untill the plaintiff be inabled, to ſue he muſt together with his plea produce the record which warranteth the ſame.</p>
               <p>If the Defendant after he hath appeared and taken a copy of the Bill, findeth that he can not make anſwer to the ſame without ſight of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:125850:76"/>
his evidence, which are in the country far off or if there be more then one defendant, and, one or more appear, and the reſt do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and the defendants that do appear can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwer without conference with the reſt that are in the country upon <hi>Affidavit</hi> made upon ſuch or the like allegations, he may have time to anſwer, untill the beginning of the next Term, either in perſon, or by commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the court ſhall think fit.</p>
               <p>Or if <hi>Affidavit</hi> be made, that the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant is aged, impotent or ſick, and not able to travell, he may have a commiſſion to take his anſwer, and ſometimes when the Defendants dwell far off, the court, in favour doth grant a commiſſion without any <hi>Affidavit,</hi> to take their anſwer in the country, in all which caſes where a commiſſion is granted for the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, the plaintiff may name one or two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, to ſee the defendant ſworn to his anſwer, &amp; a promiſe muſt be in the commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Plaintiff or his commiſſioners ſhal have notice of the day and place of execution thereof certain dayes before.</p>
               <p>If the Defendant have matter to plead to an Engliſh bill, and be not able to come to put that in upon oath, he may by ſpeciall order of the Court, have a commiſſion to take his plea
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:125850:76"/>
and the plaintiff may proceed upon plea, as upon anſwer, if he think good, but if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant have the favor to take his anſwer or plea, he may not after put in a demurrer.</p>
               <p>If the matter of the bill be releived againſt a ſuit, at or in the Eccleſiaſticall court, and the Defendant ſtand in contempt, either for not appearing or not anſwering, or if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have a commiſſion to take his anſwer, the court upon the motion of the plaintiff, doth uſuall ſtay the Defendants proceedings untill he have anſwered another order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon taken either by injunction or order of the court.</p>
               <p>If the Defendant be ſerved with proceſſe to appear to a bill and be in priſon, and will not appear, or if he do appear and be in priſon, and will not anſwer, the court doth uſually order, that he ſhall be kept cloſe priſoner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he yeild obedience to the Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quoere</hi> in the cauſe whether the Defendant hath appeared and will not anſwer (as in the Chancery &amp; Star Chamber) the Court will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree the matter againſt him for confeſſed, that were to be ſeen if here be any order therefore made to the contrary in any argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or debate in the matter, and what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:125850:77"/>
there ſhould be of a contrary courſe in this Court.</p>
               <p>After the Defendant hath anſwered (or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if there be good cauſe) the Court doth grant injunctions, either by quieting of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſionor, ſtay of ſuits at the common Law, and the Eccleſiaſticall courts untill the hearing of the cauſe, alſo there be preſidents for ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuits in the ſtar chamber and Chaneery and other courts of equity.</p>
               <p>If the Defendant put in a demurrer with an anſwer over to the matter of the bill, the plaintiff may proceed upon that to bring the cauſe to hearing, and the Defendant at the hearing, may ſtand upon the demurrer, untill the Court do over rule that, but after the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer put in, the Court will allow no excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Juriſdiction.</p>
               <p>When the Defendant hath fully anſwered, the plaintiff may if he will go to hearing upon bill, and anſwer, and may move the Court to have a day of hearing appointed, and ſerve the defendant with proceſſe to attend the hearing. In which caſe he muſt admit the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants anſwer to be true in all things, as well in that which is denyed, as that which is confeſſed.</p>
               <p>If the Plaintif do not find matter confeſſed by the Defendant in his anſwer whereupon he
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:125850:77"/>
may proceed to hearing, without proofs, then he muſt reply to the ſame, maintaining his bil and denying and traverſing the materiall points of the anſwer, wherein he may alſo add ſuch further matter as ſhal be pertinent &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him to prefer for the ſtrengthning of his bill, and avoiding the Defendants an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and muſt ſerve the Defendant with proceſs of <hi>Subpoena</hi> to rejoyn to the ſaid repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, except the Defendant be ordered to rejoyn gratis, as ſometimes that is ordered when the Defendant hath the favour to have a commiſſion to take his anſwer.</p>
               <p>When the cauſe cometh to hearing upon bill and anſwer, and the court ſeeth no ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient matter confeſſed in the anſwer to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon, the Plaintiff may deſire, that he may reply and proceed to proceſſe, and the court allow him to do ſo, eſpecially where the Kings Attorney is plaintiff for the King.</p>
               <p>If there be more defendants then one, and they put in ſeverall anſwers, the plaintiff may reply to them all in one replication, but if the cauſe of ſuit be joynt, and ſome of them an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and others do delay their anſwers, the plaintiff may not reply till all have anſwered, for if he do, he ſhall wave his proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the reſt, and he cannot have a decree
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:125850:78"/>
againſt ſome without the others. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs if the cauſes of ſuit be ſeverall the plaintif may reply and proceed to hearing with ſome, and after return to proceed with the reſt.</p>
               <p>When the defendant cometh to rejoyn, if here be no new matter in the replication, he is to make his rejoynder of courſe to maintain his anſwer, and it is not neceſſary that he ſhould rejoin but for formality, but if here be new matter in the replication, he muſt rejoin ſpecially to that, and likewiſe if there ariſe new matter in the defendants rejoynder, the Plaintiff muſt ſurjoyn, and ſo as long as new matter doth pertinently ariſe in the pleading, they muſt proceed with Rebutter, and ſur-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butter, untill every point materiall be put in perfect iſſue.</p>
               <p>After they are at iſſue, the plaintiff if he will may proceed to hearing, upon Records, and without examination of witneſſes, and the Defendant nevertheleſs, may examine witneſſes if he will in convenient time, or if there have been any former examinations in the ſame cauſe, either between the ſame par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or any other under whom they claim, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame Court or any other, the plaintif or the defendant may move the Court and deſire to have them allowed, to be uſed
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:125850:78"/>
for evidence at the hearing, in which caſe, the Court doth give a day to the other ſide, and upon hearing of both ſides, do allow or diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, as is then thought fit and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they may prepare themſelves for proofs more or leſſe.</p>
               <p>When the defendant is ſerved with proceſs to rejoyn, and doth not appear, the plaintiff upon <hi>Affidavit</hi> made in the Term time of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the proceſs (if there be no new matter in the replication) may have a commiſſion alone if the defendant will not joyn within a certain time, and then the plaintiff may have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to ſuch as he ſhall nominate to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his witneſſe.</p>
               <p>If both parties joyn in commiſſion, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide is to name indifferent commiſſioners and each party to chooſe two of the four na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the other, and the commiſſion is to be directed to thoſe four agreed upon, and the plaintiff is to have the carriage of the commiſſion, and is to give fourteene dayes warning (or ſuch other warning as is agreed upon) of the day and place of execution thereof, except there be day and place appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the commiſſion, which ſometimes is done by agreement of the parties or by order of the Court.
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:125850:79"/>
If the one ſide wil examin witneſſes by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and the other will not, yet he that will not examine may joyn in commiſſion to ſee an indifferent examination if he will, and to that end ſhall have warning of a day and place.</p>
               <p>If the Defendant make default, and do not joyn in commiſſion at the firſt, yet if he come afterwards, and can ſhew any reaſonable cauſe, why he did not joyn before, the Court will allow him to examin his witneſſes in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable time, or if a commiſſion be taken out by one or both ſides, and not executed, but in part executed, where there is no wilfull default in the parties, but by ſome other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the execution is prevented, the Court upon motion and proof of the allegations will grant a new commiſſion, but if either party will wilfully neglect to examin for delay, and to gain time, or to hearken and learn what hath been examined and proved on the other ſide, that he may the better prepare his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and interrogatories for a croſſe exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, in ſuch caſes the Court will give no favour to the party that ſhall ſo willingly or purpoſely be negligent.</p>
               <p>In ſuch caſe where the one ſide hath exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all his witneſſes, and the other hath not,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:125850:79"/>
but hath the favour to have a new Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that party that examined, may joyn in a new commiſſion without charges, to ſee the Examination.</p>
               <p>As the parties may examin their witneſſes before Commiſſioners, ſo they may likewiſe examin before the Barons in Court, ſuch wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes as they have in town at any time before publication. and they may have proceſs of <hi>Subpoena</hi> to bring their witneſſes before the Barons to be examined, and the like proceſs or the Commiſſioners Warrant to bring their witneſſes before the Commiſſioners the names of ſuch witneſſes as are examined in Court, muſt be delivered by either ſide, to the parties or their Attornyes in Court before their exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, to the end that either ſide may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min him if they will.</p>
               <p>The partys that will examin witneſſes, muſt prepare their interrogatories ingroſſed in parchment to be exhibited before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, the Baron before whom they will examin before any examination can be had, which interrogatories muſt be drawn accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to points in iſſue, by the bill and anſwer, and other pleadings, and they muſt not examin upon any thing that is not in the pleadings, if they do, that is to be ſurpreſſed, and there
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:125850:80"/>
muſt be no alteration of any interrogatories, nor addition of any, after the firſt examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but if there be further examination that muſt be upon the ſame Interrogatories that were firſt exhibited, and if any examination be taken otherwiſe, it muſt be ſuppreſſed whether it be by commiſſion or in Court, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be ſo appointed by ſome ſpeciall order of the Court.</p>
               <p>If a witneſs be examined of one ſide, and after be ſerved with proceſs to be examined on the other ſide, and do refuſe to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Court will not allow his depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be uſed, becauſe he hath ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be partiall.</p>
               <p>After the witneſſes be examined, there muſt be order for publication of their depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, either by conſent of both ſides, or by motion of the one ſide, and a day given to the other ſide to ſhew cauſe why they ſhould not be publiſhed, and the cauſe heard, at which day if nothing be ſayd to the contrary, they are publiſhed, and the cauſe is to be ſet down afterwards for the hearing, at ſuch time as the Lord Treaſurer and the Barons ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point.</p>
               <p>After the day of hearing is ſet down, the Plaintiſſ muſt ſerve the Defendant with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:125850:80"/>
of <hi>Subpana, Ad audiendum judicium,</hi> returnable at a day and place appointed for the hearing, and in the mean time either party is to prepare his breviates, of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and proofs to inſtruct his counſell.</p>
               <p>At which day the bill of cauſes is to be made ready and delivered to the Lord Treaſurer, Chancellor, and Barons in Court, wherein the cauſes are to be ſet down in order as they were appointed, and ſo the Court doth call for them, as they lye in the bill, and if both ſides be ready to proceed to hearing, the Plaintiffs counſell opening the materiall parts of the bill, and the Defendants counſell ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his anſwer, and after debating thereof on both ſides, for the full opening to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in queſtion the plaintiff is to make his proofs. which are to be read by his Attorney in court, and the defendant is to do the like, whereupon the Court doth judge, <hi>Secundum allegata &amp; probata,</hi> as if there be good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alledged, and ſet forth in the bill and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and ſufficiently proved there by confeſſion of the defendant in his anſwer, or by witneſſes, Records, or other evidence which cannot be diſapproved by the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, the Court doth make a decree for the plaintiff, but if there be good matter ſet forth,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:125850:81"/>
and not proved, or good matter proved, but not ſet forth in the pleadings, the Defendant and the cauſe is diſmiſſed.</p>
               <p>Sometimes the cauſe is diſmiſſed upon ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for want of ſufficient matter, or for that it is meerly tryable at the Common Law, and ſometimes when there is both matter of Law and Equity, the matter of Law is referred to a tryall at the Exchequer bar, and the equity of the cauſe is retained untill the hearing, and ſometimes when the queſtion is touching ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts and reckonings which are intricate, the cauſe is referred to auditors or Merchants by Commiſſion to examin and try the ſame, and to mediate and end and determin if they can, or elſe to certfie the Court of their doing, whereupon the Court may further proceed) or if the queſtion be concerning the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any lands demanded by the plaintiff which ly intermingled and diſperſed with and amongſt the Defendants lands, and by reaſon of a long and joynt occupation cannot well be known or diſtinguiſhed, the one from the other, in ſuch caſe when that it appeareth to the Court that the plaintiff hath and ought to have Land ſo intermingled, the Court doth award a commiſſion to the Gentry of that County where the Land lyeth, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:125850:81"/>
the certainty thereof, and to ſet out, &amp; the metes and bounds of the ſame, and to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Court thereof, and in ſuch like caſes References and Commiſſions are awarded.</p>
               <p>If at the day of hearing the plaintiff be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the Defendant maketh default <hi>affida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit</hi> is to be made of the ſerving, the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant with proceſs, <hi>ad audiendum judicium,</hi> and the Court will proceed to hearing, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the plaintiffs bill be opened, the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants anſwer is to be read, and the plaintiffs proofs, whereupon the Court will decree or diſmiſſe the cauſe, or otherwiſe order that as ſhall ſeem fit but in ſuch caſe the Court doth not uſe to make a decree abſolute, but to give a day to the Defendant to ſhew what he can againſt that, at which day if he do come and endeavour to ſhew cauſe to ſtay the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and thereupon the Court doth proceed, and further hearing the plaintiff may require coſts for his double attendance, by reaſon of the Defendants default.</p>
               <p>If the Defendant be ready at the day of hearing, and the plaintiff make default, the Court doth diſmiſſe the Defendant with coſts, except ſome good cauſe be ſhewed to ſtay that, and if that be put over till another day, the plaintiff is to pay coſts to the Defendant, ſuch as the Court ſhall think fit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:125850:82"/>
When the Defendant is once ſerved with proceſs, <hi>Ad audiendum judicium,</hi> although the cauſe cannot be heard at that time, or in that Term, he muſt attend without any more proceſs, untill the cauſe be heard, ſo long as the cauſe be continued in the bill of cauſes; but if the plaintiff be negligent, and will not endure to procure a hearing, but deſire to continue that in the bill, to keep an injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on foot, or to ſtay the Defendants courſe at the common Law, or in any other Court, the Defendant may move for a diſmiſſion of the cauſe, and the injunction may be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and that he may have coſts.</p>
               <p>Alſo if the plaintiff after anſwer put into his bill will delay the proſecution thereof, the Defendant may move to be diſmiſſed with coſts, whereupon the Court will find a day to ſhew cauſe.</p>
               <p>When a cauſe is ready for hearing, if the plaintiff delay the proſecution, or be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to procure a hearing, the Defendant may if he will, procure the cauſe to be ſet for hearing, and ſerve the plaintiff with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, <hi>ad audiendum judicium,</hi> At which day, if the plaintiff will appear, he may proceed to hearing, but if he will not, the Defendant may be diſmiſſed with coſts, and left at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:125850:82"/>
if there were any injunction or order to reſtrain him.</p>
               <p>If a Defendant dye after anſwer put in, and before the cauſe be determined, the plaintiff may put in a bill of Revivor againſt the heir, or Executor, or Adminiſtrator of the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, as the caſe ſhall require, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant in ſuch bill of Revivor, ſhall anſwer without oath, becauſe his anſwer is to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end but to ſubmit himſelf to the former proceedings and upon his anſwer the former proceedings are revived, and ſhall ſtand in the ſame caſe as they did againſt the firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant that dyed, and the plaintiff and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant may proceed further to bring the cauſe to hearing, in that ſame manner as that ſhould have been proceeded in, if the firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant had lived, and in like, when the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff dyeth pendent like.</p>
               <p>After a decree is made and paſt againſt the Defendant, if he hath other matter which was not in iſſue in the cauſe decreed, which he ſuppoſeth will be ſufficient to overthrow the decree, he may exhibit a bill of Review upon that new matter, to reverſe the decree, but he muſt perform the decree, and yeild obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that, and if the bill of Review do not contain good and ſufficient matter, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:125850:83"/>
may plead the former matter, decreed in bar, of the proceedings upon the new bill, and that is not ſufficient for the plaintif in the bill of Review to produce new proofs though never ſo good, that were not produced before, but the matter muſt not be ſuch matter as was not in the iſſue before, and he may likewiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit his bill of Review of error in the former proceedings.</p>
               <p>Sometimes the principall queſtion between the partyes is ſuch, as admitting the truth of both ſides, yet it is doubtfull in Law to whom the Right belongeth, ſo as the Court cannot make a decree untill the matter in Law be determined, whereupon a caſe in Law is to be drawn and agreed upon of both ſides, and if there be any matter of fact neceſſary to be proved for the making of the caſe, witneſſes may be examined upon Interrogatories for that purpoſe, and when the caſe is agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeverall Copies muſt be delivered to the Lord Treaſurer, Chancellor, and Barons, and is to be argued on both ſides, when, and as often as the Court ſhall think fit, and ſo be determined by decree or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Sometimes when publication is over haſtily gotten by the plaintiff before the Defendant hath fully examined his witneſſes, the Court
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:125850:83"/>
upon <hi>affidavit</hi> by the Defendant, that neither he nor any for him hath ſeen the depoſitions of the witneſſes, doth admit him to examine ſuch witneſſes, as he hath to examine.</p>
               <p>Upon hearing of a cauſe, the Court doth allow Bills and anſwers, and other pleadings and orders and decrees of the Chancery, and other Courts, to be read for evidence, without any order of allowance, but no depoſitions of witneſſes taken in any other Court, nor in another cauſe in the ſame Court, without ſpeciall order.</p>
               <p>And ſomtimes (but very rarely) after publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of both ſides, the Court doth allow them to examine witneſſes <hi>(ad informandum conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam)</hi> in which caſe the depoſitions that be taken, are not to be publiſhed but onely ſeen by the Court.</p>
               <p>After a Decree is entred, that may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled and exemplified at the inſtance of either party, or of any elſe that deſire that</p>
               <p>If the poſſeſſion of any Land be decreed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Defendant, the plaintiff may have an Injunction directed to him, and all that claim under him, commanding him and them to remove from the poſſeſſion, and to yeild the ſame to the plaintiff and his Aſſignes, and if the Defendants diſobey that, the Court up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>affidavit</hi> made thereof doth uſually grant
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:125850:84"/>
an injunction directed to the Sheriff to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him, and to put the plaintiff in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>If a decree be in any thing diſobeyed, either by the plaintiff or Defendant, or any other by their procurement, upon <hi>affidavit</hi> thereof made, an attachment is granted againſt ſuch as have diſobeyed, another proceſs of contempt untill he be brought into Court to anſwer his contempt, and when he doth appear, if he deny the contempt alledged againſt him in the <hi>affid.</hi> he muſt be examined upon Interrogatories, to be exhibited by the proſecutor of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, before one of the Barons, which muſt be upon the points mentioned in the <hi>affida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit,</hi> and he muſt be enjoyned by the Court, to attend and appear from day to day untill he be examined, and not to depart without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe of the Court, or if the Court think fit he is to be bound by Recognizance to the ſame purpoſe. After he is examined, if he have confeſſed ſufficient matter of contempt, the proſecutor muſt move the court to appoint a day to hear his examinations, at which day, both ſides are to attend, and ſuch of the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations to be read as are materiall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon if that appear to the Court, that he hath ommitted any contempt worthy to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:125850:84"/>
the Court doth commit him to the Fleet and may impoſe a fine upon him, or not, as the caſe requireth, where he is to remain du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the pleaſure of the Court, and untill he yeild obedience, and ſubmit himſelfe to the Court to perform the decree, or enter into Recognizance to perform the ſame, if the Court ſo think fit, and he is to pay ſuch coſts to the proſecutor, as the Court ſhall taxe.</p>
               <p>If the Defendant upon his examination de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the contempt ſuppoſed againſt him, he may move the Court to be diſcharged with coſts, whereupon the proſecutor may deſire to examine witneſſes to prove the contempt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in court, or by commiſſion. In which caſe if the proſecutor take a commiſſion, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant may deſire to joyn in commiſſion, to ſee a due examination of witneſſes, but not to examin any witneſſes except the Court doth ſpecially order it ſo, after which examination the Court doth appoint a day of hearing, at the motion of the proſecutor, or of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, to convict or diſcharge the defendant as the caſe ſhall then appeare</p>
               <p>And the like courſe is held for puniſhing or diſcharging of contempts, ſuppoſed againſt the proceſs of the court, if the caſe ſo require.</p>
               <p>A Bill may be amended by order of the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:125850:85"/>
Court, after the Defendant hath anſwered that upon payment of coſts.</p>
               <p>In all caſes that are ordinary, the Court doth uſe to have the counſell of both ſides, &amp; thereupon to make ſuch order as the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
               <p>In every long vacation all the bills, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, Replications, Rejoynders, and other pleadings are to be taken from the common files, and all the pleadings in one cauſe are to be filed together with the Bill, by him that is towards the Bill, and to be entred in a booke kept for that purpoſe, in the title of that County, where the matter of ſuit ariſeth, and to be numbred, and then filed, according to the number on the file for the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>In caſes of extraordinary contempts, the Court doth ſometimes ſend a Meſſenger or a Serjeant at Armes to apprehend and bring in the Offender.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:125850:85"/>
                  <head>THE TABLE, Augmentation,</head>
                  <item>ARticles of the Court of augmentations, 119 ad 129</item>
                  <item>When united to the Exchequer, 120</item>
                  <item>Lord Treaſurers power thereby, 15</item>
                  <item>The Cheife Barons power thereby, 28</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Attorney,</hi> The Kings Attorney, his office place and power 39 63 88 ad 94</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Accounts,</hi> Scroul of accounts, what and by whom kept 56 73</item>
                  <item>Forfeitures thereupon 59</item>
                  <item>Auditors of the Exchequer, their office and duty 95</item>
                  <item>Attorneyes and Clarks in the Kings Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers office, 95</item>
                  <item>In the Pipe 96</item>
                  <item>In the office of pleas 97</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:125850:86"/>
                  <item>Attachment in the Exchequer, and when 139</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Anſwer,</hi> What time to anſwer in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer 140</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>B.</head>
                  <item>LOrd cheif Baron of the Exchequer, his office and power 23 24 26 27</item>
                  <item>How and where he giveth judgement 25</item>
                  <item>What he may do out of Court 26</item>
                  <item>Second Baron, his office place and power 29 30</item>
                  <item>What accounts he may take, 31</item>
                  <item>Third Baron, his office, place and power 32</item>
                  <item>What accounts he takes, 33</item>
                  <item>Fourth Baron, his office, place, and power, 34 35</item>
                  <item>What accounts he takes 36 37</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>C.</head>
                  <item>CHancellor of the Exchequer, his office and place 19 20</item>
                  <item>Commiſſions awarded in open Court 25</item>
                  <item>Chamberlains, two, their office place and power, 37 38</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Communia,</hi> what it is 60</item>
                  <item>Cuſtomer, their a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>counts where to be entred 73</item>
                  <item>Controller of the Pipe his office 85</item>
                  <item>Chamberlain, Under Chamberlains two, their
<pb facs="tcp:125850:86"/>
Office and power 117</item>
                  <item>Crown, Court of Revenues, Sheriffs articles annexed to the Court of Exchequer at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> 119</item>
                  <item>Content of the ſaid articles 119 120 and 129</item>
                  <item>Coſts, when, and for what payable 139</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>D.</head>
                  <item>DEcree, who may make decrees in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer 567</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dies datus,</hi> what 5658</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>De debitis plurimum,</hi> what 71</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>De pluribus debitis,</hi> what Ibid.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>E.</head>
                  <item>EScheator, <hi>Nomina Eſcaetor.</hi> what 65</item>
                  <item>Their account, where entred 72</item>
                  <item>Engliſh Bills in Exchequer, and the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings thereupon 136 ad fin.</item>
                  <item>What may be ſued for there, and by, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom 137</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>F.</head>
                  <item>FInes upon informations, by whom ſet, and where tis chargeable. 28 29</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:125850:87"/>
                  <item>Who may be fined and when, 61</item>
                  <item>Fifteens, how to be accounted for, and where, 74</item>
                  <item>Fee-farm Rents, upon whom chargeable 77</item>
                  <item>First fruits and Tenths, the Remembrancer thereof 84</item>
                  <item>The Court thereof united to the Exchequer, 129</item>
                  <item>The Articles of uniting 129 ad 136</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>H.</head>
                  <item>HOmage, reſpit of homage, what 64</item>
                  <item>Fines for it, and by whom payable, 64 65</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <item>JUſtices of Peace, their wages, how, and by whom payable 81 82</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>M.</head>
                  <item>MOney, warrants for mony, by whom made and to whom, and for what, 10 11 13 16</item>
                  <item>Marſhall of the Exchequer, his office and duty, 104 105</item>
                  <item>Meſſengers of the receit, their office 118</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:125850:87"/>
                  <head>N</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>NEC non ad oſtendendum,</hi> what, and the progreſſe therein 62</item>
                  <item>Admittance thereupon, by whom 62</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nomina Vic.</hi> What 65</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nihil,</hi> Clerks of the <hi>Nihils,</hi> his office 81: 101</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>O Blata,</hi> what and upon whom chargeable 78</item>
                  <item>Oppoſer, Forraine Oppoſer, what, and his office 80. 87</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <item>PRoffers in the exchequer, what, to whom made, and when forfeited 54. 55. 58.</item>
                  <item>Rolls of proffers, by whom kept 54.</item>
                  <item>Pipe, <hi>Schedula pipe,</hi> what 66.</item>
                  <item>Clerk of the pipe, his office 66 67</item>
                  <item>Preſts, <hi>Auditor</hi> of the preſts, what, and his office 83 84</item>
                  <item>Pleas, Clerk of the pleas, his office 86 87</item>
                  <item>Parcellmakers 2. their office and duty 99</item>
                  <item>Prayſors of the Court, who, their office 106</item>
                  <item>Pelle, Clerk thereof, his office and duty 111</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:125850:88"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pellis recepti, &amp; pellis exitus,</hi> What 111</item>
                  <item>Controller thereof, his office 112</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>R.</head>
                  <item>REmembrancer, Kings Remembrancer, his office duty and power, 40 443 244 45 ad 53</item>
                  <item>Who are accountable before him 41</item>
                  <item>Treaſurers Remembrancer, his office, place, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and power, 53 ad 70</item>
                  <item>Records, when to be made up cleer 69</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rotulus examinatus,</hi> who 75 76</item>
                  <item>His office and duty 76</item>
                  <item>Receivers, their office and duty 94</item>
                  <item>Receit, Auditor thereof his office 113 ad 116</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>S.</head>
                  <item>STreats, by whom receivable 68</item>
                  <item>Clark of the Streats, his office <hi>ibid.</hi> 69 82</item>
                  <item>Sheriff, for what he is chargeable, as to himſelf or predeceſſor upon account, 71 72 79 81</item>
                  <item>Subſidies how to be accounted for, and where 74</item>
                  <item>Solicitor, Kings Sollicitor, his office, place and power; 94</item>
                  <item>Surveyors their office and duty 95</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:125850:88"/>
                  <item>Seal of the Court, what 102 103</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <item>TReaſurer, Lord Treaſurer his office 217</item>
                  <item>How made 12</item>
                  <item>How far, and to what his power extends in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall things 3 4 6 7 8 9 1 2</item>
                  <item>Tallyes, joyners thereof, their office and duty, and cutters thereof 98 112</item>
                  <item>Tellers of the Exchequer four, their offices and dutyes 107 108 109 110</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>U</head>
                  <item>UNder Treaſurer, his office &amp; power 21 22</item>
                  <item>When firſt made, and who 21</item>
                  <item>Uſher, chief Uſher his office and duty 103 104</item>
                  <item>Ordinary Uſhers, their office and duties 105</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>W</head>
                  <item>WOod Sales, who may make them 10</item>
                  <item>Roll of Writs, what and by whom kept, 56</item>
                  <item>Wardrobe, <hi>Magna guardrobe roll,</hi> what 75</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:125850:89"/>
            <head>
               <hi>June</hi> 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1658.</head>
            <p>HAving peruſed this diſcourſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's inviolable Authority, Certainty and Truth, I find it (in its proportion) as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf is, <hi>profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs;</hi> and therefore Judge it very uſeful, to confront the Blaſphemy of bold Antiſcripturiſts, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the weak in Faith, and to raiſe the value of (which cannot be overvalued) the Holy Scripture in the hearts of all true Beleevers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſeph Caril.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Unto this atteſtation, given by my Reverend Brother, I willingly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe.
EDM. CALAMY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
